<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The illustrious shepherdess. Dedicated to the Marchioness of Dorchester.</title>
            <title>Successos y prodigias de amor. Book 5. English</title>
            <author>Pérez de Montalván, Juan, 1602-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1588_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 201:E1588[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The illustrious shepherdess. Dedicated to the Marchioness of Dorchester.</title>
                  <title>Successos y prodigias de amor. Book 5. English</title>
                  <author>Pérez de Montalván, Juan, 1602-1638.</author>
                  <author>Phillips, Edward, 1630-1696?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Nath. Brook, at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of book 5 of: Pérez de Montalván, Juan. Successos y prodigias de amor.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: E.P. [i.e. Edward Phillips].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The second 6 in the imprint has been crossed out and replaced with a "5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170135:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ILLUSTRIOUS SHEPHERDESS.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to the MARCHIONESS OF <hi>DORCHESTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Nath. Brook,</hi> at the Angel in Cornhil, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170135:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170135:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, THE MARCHIONESS OF <hi>DORCHESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince if the beauty of <hi>Mandana,</hi> the Charming Modeſty of <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyra,</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Mariamne;</hi> (and, which is more than all theſe, ſince ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:170135:3"/>hath had the honour to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by a perſon, as conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his title, as the exaltedneſs of his Minde and Spirit, to a Lady of reſembling quality) the high attractions of <hi>Partheniſſa:</hi> if all that hath been mention'd Great and Vertuous in all the Stories that have yet been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, were contracted into One, to make a reſemblance of your divine Perfections, they would yet fall ſhort to expreſs them: I am induc'd to believe, That to preſent your Honour with this piece of imperfection, can be but the ſame preſumption as to have interrupted your more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant diverſions with any thing
<pb facs="tcp:170135:3"/>of the moſt refin'd and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd that ever Courted Fame: it being the Prerogative of Greatneſs, to confer that value upon meaner things out of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which even the greateſt could not be capable to obtain by deſert: Nor could this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign have confeſs'd its deficiency by a nobler way, than by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring ſo bright an influence: and thoſe things which pretend to higheſt conſummation, ſhould they ground their Dignitie upon their own Compleatneſſe, they would become as much unworthy your Condeſcention, as to obtain what they pretend to; they would ſtand in need of it, and
<pb facs="tcp:170135:4"/>thereby diveſt themſelves of their moſt glorious Title, which is to admire, and wait upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies greater than any themſelves could ſhew: for it were a groſſe ſtupidity, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration being the inſeparable Concomitant of thoſe infinite Glories and Beauties which ſhine in your Soul, and throw a Radiant Luſtre round about you, if our Reſentments ſhould not be as High as the Cauſe is Noble that produceth them: Had you only deriv'd thoſe vast Applauds which are render'd you by all thoſe with whom Vertue hath any Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from your happie Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:170135:4"/>as being Wife to that Noble Lord, whoſe Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezza's of Spirit are ſo many, and whoſe Learning ſhines in ſo immenſe a degree, that (not only among thoſe of a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Extraction, but even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Meaner ſort of Men, who not being Conſiderable in themſelves, may haply be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to ſeek for Eminence by the Studie and Profeſsion of Arts) few have attain'd to that ſublime Perfection; and next, as Daughter to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Lady, whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Actions (great as the Fame which eternally attends upon her Memorie) not only
<pb facs="tcp:170135:5"/>tranſcend whatever hath been done of moſt Heroick, by the moſt famous of her Sex in all Ages, but even Romances themſelves, whoſe Cuſtom it is to deſcribe Actions as boundleſs as Fancy can ſuggeſt, have not produc'd Examples more Illuſtrious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their moſt exalted <hi>Hero</hi>'s; this were a Condition glorious enough to Cover you with more Palms than the world affords: And although there is no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration equally powerful with the heighth of thoſe Actions, to tranſmit the Glory of them to Posterity; yet to decline the payment of the higheſt Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes I could be capable of
<pb facs="tcp:170135:5"/>rendring unto the Monument of ſo much Worth and Glory, would be a Neglect as Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, as the Celebration of them a Duty. I ſhall not at preſent longer inſiſt upon the Elogium's of thoſe Illuſtrious Perſonages, although they are ſo juſt, that all tongues might ambition to dwell upon them; leſt I might ſeem to make you redevable for thoſe Honors, which are the rightful Effects of your own inherent Worth, unto thoſe Excellencies which are own'd by others. But Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, There are in your ſelf advantages of ſo high a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Vertues ſo bright and
<pb facs="tcp:170135:6"/>unacceſsional, which make you owe your Concernment in thoſe glorious Relations, more to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit than to Fortune; that the Paſsion I have to Adore them, is yet more powerful than what might render the confidence of this Addreſs pardonable: Yet ſince I repreſented to my ſelf how much your Actions are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Vulgar Applauds, the Apprehenſion of how unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a Title I had to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Rendring them, had almoſt ſubdued my Inclination to an abſolute Declining of ſo great an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, had not a firme reſolve rather to hazzard the Committing of ſo
<pb facs="tcp:170135:6"/>conſiderable a Crime, than not to expreſs the Adoration I have for Vertue, eſpecially ſhining in ſo Illuſtrious a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, made me reaſſume my firſt Intention: And I confeſs, the Authors Fame had not a ſmall Aſcendent upon me in this Election; Who, I believe, out of a fatal inſtinct that his Deſign would come to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before a Judgement ſo Comprehenſive, and ſo Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating a Wit, hath made his <hi>Hero</hi> to perform ſomwhat of ſo gallant, that in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Limits to which he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd, and his due regard to Likelihood and Poſsibility, a
<pb facs="tcp:170135:7"/>particular, of which there are few Romances which make any great Conſcience; I ſee not how he could have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd more. And whether we look on <hi>Silvia,</hi> dreſs'd in the innocencies and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained handſomneſs of a Paſtoral Converſation, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the more reſplendent gentilleſſes of her true Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I am confident ſhe will think her ſelf more Fortunate in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing held worthy of your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, than in the bare Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction ſhe could derive from either of theſe Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Since in the former, there are no becomingneſſes
<pb facs="tcp:170135:7"/>which are not in you ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, as if thoſe happy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were return'd, wherein, to be a Princeſs and to be a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſs, were the ſelf-ſame thing: and in the later, ſhe is ſo darkned and exceeded by a more ſurpaſsing ſplendor, that the greateſt Priviledge ſhe can aſpire to, is to court the protection of a Greatneſs that ſo much out-ſhines her. Nor can I think my ſelf indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently concern'd in <hi>Silvia's</hi> Contentment, ſeeing the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of preſenting her is not to be equall'd by any thing, but by the Humility and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion wherewith ſhe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb facs="tcp:170135:8"/>to ſo unſpeakable a Felicity, By</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honours moſt Humble, moſt Obedient, and moſt Faithful Servant, <hi>E. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170135:8"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas our Nation hath been ſo profuſely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd, and perhaps by this time in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Satiated by the fluency and luxuriance of the French Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; it will not be amiſs to give a taſte of the Spaniſh Reſerve and Gravity: And (ſince things of this nature are ſwell'd to ſuch an exceſſe of voluminouſneſs) to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect one extream with another, by publiſhing an Adventure as conciſe
<pb facs="tcp:170135:9"/>as the reſt are tedious. How they may relliſh abroad, I will not think my ſelf oblig'd to any ſtrict regard: it is enough for me to ſay, <hi>Montal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van</hi> was the Author; And that two others of the ſame original, <hi>Aurora,</hi> and <hi>The Prince,</hi> were long ſince thought worthy to be render'd by Mr. <hi>Stanly,</hi> a perſon of conſiderable Worth and Quality; whoſe Fame, if it be a ſtranger to any, it is only to ſuch who are not much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in Learning or Ingenuity: and whatever advantages they may juſtly claim above theſe, I am not troubled to be out-done by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as much beyond me in Merit, as in Fame.</p>
            <p>Whatever Peccadillo's may have Eſcap'd in Printing, the Readers judgment may Correct; only I thought fit to give this Precaution, That in the Firſt Page in ſtead of <hi>ſhares</hi> is to be read <hi>ſhines:</hi> And in Page 12 the <hi>Comma</hi> after <hi>Woman</hi> ſhould have been after <hi>undaunted.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170135:9"/>
            <head>The Illuſtrious Shepherdeſs.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Heaven had new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diplay'd it's blue Canopie, beſprinkled with innumerous fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Gems; and that fair Star that leads up all the reſt, and ſhares the glory of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, was ſo profuſe of her Rayes, that it might well have been thought that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Sun was not ſet, or elſe that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sun had ſucceeded in his room, and night, to whom he had ſurrendred his place, as to his lawful Succeſſour, repoſed in the boſome of her beloved ſilence; when <hi>Albanius</hi> leaving his little Flock of Sheep to feaſt themſelves upon the ſprouting dainties of the Field, retir'd himſelf to Contemplate the misfortunes of his paſt life. For though he was now
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170135:10"/>advanced in years, yet he ſtill retain'd a Paſſion, which in the ſummer of his age had taken poſſeſſion of his heart, having married a fair Shepherdeſſe, with whom he liv'd in a faſhion ſo tender and reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as is not to be expreſs'd: (For Love, not always a Courtier, oft-times vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes the ruſtick Villages his preſence) but he had not been Married above two years, before her death depriv'd him of the ſole felicity of his life, leaving him the moſt diſconſolate man on earth: he ſate neer to the brink of a cleer Brook, which with it's feet of ſilver, trampling upon the ſands of gold, delighted to flow along ſo many banks of Roſes, and convey'd the moiſture of life to ſome certain little trees, that truſting to the ſwiftneſſe of their growth, made full account (ere ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Springs had flouriſh'd) to become the Giants of the Wood. Here the good Shepherd diverted his minde with the thoughts of his former felicity, refreſhing himſelf with thoſe thoughts, the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the flowers, and the wanton pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the cryſtal waves; when not far from the place where he ſate, he heard a ſhrill voice, that with many ſighs and ſobs, often call'd upon Death; of which, not leſſe ſweet than mournful, the ſportful
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170135:10"/>
               <hi>Zephyrets</hi> were enamour'd; and for the love of that ſound, ſtood playing the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with the trembling leaves. <hi>Albanius</hi> aroſe, having his Soul touch'd with a tender compaſſion: for he had not a breſt where pity was denied to harbour, nor was his Soul ſo baſe as to give it ſelf up to fear: he was of a generous ſpirit, though a Shepherd; and full of compaſſion, though the Inhabitant of a rural Cottage: Muſing with himſelf what ſhould be the matter, he directed his courſe along the margent of the Rivoler, toward the place from whence thoſe doleful accents ſeem'd firſt to pierce his eare and his heart. He drew neer to a little Iſland, crown'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with trees ſo thick ſet together, that Day had in it but a ſmall juriſdiction. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t'ring into it, and wandring a while in that delightful darkneſſe, he came to the place where there ſate a Lady of a preſence both lovely and majeſtick; who, with the pangs of Child-birth that had but juſt left her, was ſo diſmay'd, that ſhe ſeem'd to have forgot whether ſhe liv'd or no: he drew nigh to her, and found her no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe accompanied, than with an infinite number of perplexities, &amp; that little crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but newly deliver'd from it's former habitation, which enjoy'd no other ſhelter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170135:11"/>than what the green boughs afforded; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up the babe in his arms, he cheriſh'd it, wrapt it in his warm Mantle, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it from the bleak violence of the night; then he apply'd himſelf to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was half dead with anguiſh and amazement; awak'd her out of her ſhort death, offered his beſt aſſiſtance, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor'd to comfort her with friendly and courteous language.</p>
            <p>The Lady took much notice of the Shepherds charitable uſage, and look'd upon his arrival as an accident or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd by Heaven for the redreſſe of her miſeries; and lifting herſelf up with much ado from that graſſy Couch, ſhe intreated him to accompany her to the place from whence ſhe had been taken; who ſhewed himſelf ready to ſerve her with all reſpect and civility: and ſhe, to gratifie his cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, refus'd not (as they went along the way, he having requeſted her name and quality) to ſatisfie his curioſity with the ſtory of her misfortunes.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I am (ſaid ſhe) a Woman that have the ill fortune to be accounted fair, ſince it ever happens, that the worſt of chances do ever attend on beauty. I am born of noble Parents, yet to me im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurably cruel: they reſolved in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170135:11"/>midſt of my tender years, to devote me to a Cloyſter'd life, conſulting more my obedience than my inclination; ſaying, That Children ought to ſubject their Wills to their Parents pleaſure: a Maxime perhaps not altogether void of Reaſon, if it had been ordain'd by Fate, That all minds ſhould conſent together in one Election, and not be carried on to different deſigns. But experience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms, That the Will of Man naturally deſires an abſolute Sovereignty, to have her motions free and unreſtrain'd: but I was under an Influence that threatned many croſſes to my life; for though I could obtain of my affections, to be ſway'd ſomtimes againſt the current of my Nature; yet I could never ſo totally ſubdue them, as to make them become ſubſervient in all things to my Parents intentions: nor did it avail me to ſay, That what they propoſs'd agreed not with my diſpoſition; affirming, that to alleadge this excuſe, could not acquit me from diſobedience to them; and that I offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God, by gainſaying thoſe that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd me to be his Spouſe; imputing this my adverſeneſſe to their perſwaſions, to unchaſtneſſe; and reſolv'd not to ſettle me in any condition agreeable to my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170135:12"/>own Fancy, ſince I could not content my ſelf with one of their providing. In theſe diſcontents did I dream away the flower of my youth, without the leaſt enjoyment of it. And certainly my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were to blame, for that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not that I was arriv'd to that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity of years as was not flexible to all impreſſions. I had brought my ſelf even to the point of deſpair, ſeeing theſe things fall out ſo croſly, at a time when I had yielded up my affection to a noble Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier; a man, that, for his worth, might well have deſerv'd a Lady of the greateſt fortune and extraction: the high eſteem I had of him, made me uncapable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Addreſſes with any great indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency. My Lover was very reſerv'd in his deſigns, prudent in all his actions, valiant without oſtentation, affable and courteous to all, real and fervent in his Love toward me; nor was he leſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd of me again. His opportunities of ſeeing me were very frequent, his daily walks were under my window, whereby we came to the Speech of each other; and there paſs'd not a night wherein he was not admitted into the houſe undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd by my Father or Mother: as our affections, ſo our meetings encreas'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170135:12"/>(What a hazard doth that Maid run, though never ſo circumſpect, that ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſee her lover often, much more to parley with him?) Being thus divided and wavering between the threats of my Parents, and the prayers of him I lov'd, I found a great conflict within me: this only comfort was left me, That he who was abſolute maſter of my affections, had engag'd himſelf to ſerve me with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal conſtancy and fidelity. The fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency of his viſits ſo confirm'd our loves, that at length he won me to yield him that laſt of Favours, which neither his intreaties, nor the purity of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could ever obtain, till after a Solemn Contract between us, in the preſence of two Friends, moſt faithful to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. His Father was a Gentleman of <hi>Salamanca,</hi> (a noted City, the glory of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and famous for being the foſter-Mother of noble Sciences) who had deſign'd to marry him to a Kinſwoman of his. (Parents commonly count no Matches lawful, if they be not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manag'd and concluded by their Counſels.) My Friend, loath to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe his Father, ſeem'd outwardly willing to entertain the motion; but for my ſake, ſpun out the time with many
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170135:13"/>doubts and delays. It happened about this time, that my Father being, for his eminent Learning and Deſerts taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by his Majeſty, was advanc'd to a place at Court of greateſt Honour and Profit: he glad of this unexpected pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, and intending to make his beſt advantage of it for the bettering his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, reſolv'd upon removing to that place where his occaſions requir'd him preſent: mean while, the Marriage ſo earneſtly deſir'd and endeavour'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, was diſturb'd by the arrival of my Spouſe's Father, who came him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in perſon on purpoſe to haſten his Sons return to <hi>Salamanca,</hi> that they might treat about the Match between him and that Gentlewoman, concerning whom he had ſo often writ to him; by this means I was plunged into a moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe ill plight: I durſt not make my Caſe known to my Parents; who were of that auſtere Nature, and ſo not to be perſwaded to yield to any of my deſires, that they would ſooner be brought to conſent to the taking away of my life, than not to have me confin'd to a Religious Cell: And that which made my Condition the more inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, was, That I found in my ſelf
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170135:13"/>the evident Symptoms of being with Child. So deeply did I lay to heart theſe Croſſes, that I ſought occaſions to bring my life to an end; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I ſhould have done it, but that I conſider'd, that with my own, the life of my Spouſe was in danger, and that of my Infant in certainty to be loſt: and it had been indeed a barbarous cruelty to have ſlain this innocent Creature whom as yet I have not ſeen, although it hath ſo lately coſt me innumerous pangs. The preparations for our departure I knew not well how to reſent; notwithſtanding I bore it out with the cheerfulleſt face I could, and imploy'd the deepeſt of my cunning to conceal my miſchance: at length I feign'd my ſelf extreamly ill, diſcovering the truth to the Phyſitian, that by his help, my Fiction might be the more ſecurely carried on; and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to conceal that by keeping my Bed, which I had no other way to keep un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcover'd; for all this, my Father, that made no great matter of it, and judged by my countenance, That it was rather the ſtate and delicacy of a great Dame tenderly brought up, than any real ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that caus'd me to keep my Bed, forth with intended his voyage, without
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170135:14"/>any regard to my being ill, giving me a very ſhort ſpace to prepare for the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: ſcarce had I time to diſpatch a ſhort Note to my Spouſe; wherein, with more abundance of Grief than Reaſon, I ſet forth the ſadneſſe of my Condition, the heavie affliction of our being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, and the fears and dangers that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended me: When, by that time it was mid-day, and I with much ado got rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I was hurried with the reſt out of the City; my Lover took ſilent leave of me at a diſtance, and accompanied me with his eyes as far as he could, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make me underſtand the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage they ſpake: by the cloſe of day we reach'd <hi>Pinto,</hi> a place not directly in the Road; but by reaſon of a piece of Land, which we there poſſeſſe, we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted thither. No ſooner were the reſt of our Family well ſettled in their firſt ſleep, but I perceiv'd my ſelf ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd with great pains; which were the leſſe terrible to me, becauſe my Soul was at that time as it were buried in other huge afflictions: notwithſtanding in a ſhort ſpace they encreas'd in ſuch ſort, that I plainly knew them to be the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fore-runner of my approaching la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; ſo that leaving in the Bed a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant-Maid,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170135:14"/>whom, having ever found moſt faithful to me, I had made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with my Condition; I thus ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, diſtracted, and careleſſe, having no other company but my Sorrows to attend me, betook my ſelf to this Wood, and this ſoft Bed of Flowers; which Heaven, no queſtion, out of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, leſt my ſhame ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulg'd, had made thus private; without hopes of Aid from any, ſave the ſhelter of this little tree; nor enjoying any other eaſe than my ſighs: driven hither by this neceſſity, newly disburthened (as you ſee) of this poor Infant, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt brought to the jawes of Death; here you have found me, being led hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Providence, to be the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my relief, and to ſave two lives at once; and, which is more, to protect my Honour from all violation, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying me to the place from whence I came, if that ſmall ſtrength which is yet left me, will permit me to go ſo far: or at leaſt, if the force of theſe misfortunes ſhall prevail over my life, I ſhall have obtain'd this benefit, to end my days with an unblemiſh'd Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Albanius</hi> heard theſe things, with the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170135:15"/>ſame ſeriouſneſſe ſhe related them, and was ſorrowfully affected with the ſadneſſe of theſe paſſages. The adverſity and tears of ſo delicate a perſonage, were able to force pity from Rocks, and to make rigor it ſelf not rigid. She crav'd his Name, and in what place he abided; and preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with a Purſe, enrich'd with a great number of Crowns; ſaying, <q>That ſhe would commit to his Education that little Creature, and that ſhe would take care to give her Lover notice of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; and ſeriouſly enjoyn him to recompence, to the utmoſt of his power, this great humanity of his to her and her Child.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He promis'd to perform, with all ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the truſt committed to him; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conducted her to a place not far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from her dwelling, he took his leave, admiring at the ſtrangeneſſe of this event, and eſpecially to ſee ſo undaunted a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of ſuch a ſoft and curious frame, and plunged in ſuch diſtreſſe: but what will not a generous Soul adventure, rather than ſuffer under a wounded Reputation? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning home to his Cottage, he related to his Wife (for he was again Married, although the Idea of his firſt Wives beauty could never be effaced from his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170135:15"/>memory) the whole ſtory of this Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; who, for all this, would have been apt to have entertain'd jealous imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if the Gold (than which, there is nothing more perſwaſive, and of greater Credit among men) which he brought along with him, had not ſatisfied thoſe Scruples: and calling to minde, that a few days before, one of her neereſt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours had, with ill ſucceſsful labour, brought forth a Son, which no ſooner had touch'd the threſhold of this life, but was ſnatch'd into the other world to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the number of the Angels; and thinking good to make uſe of this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, they requeſted her to Nurſe up this Child; which ſhe willingly accepted; eſteeming the ſweetneſſe, and admirable features of it, to be ſuch, as that the earth might boaſt of being enrich'd with ſuch a Seraphim: So committing it to her care, they went to buy all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the accommodation and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo dainty an Infant.</p>
            <p>While theſe things hapned in the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of <hi>Pinto,</hi> the Father of the Child having been debarr'd the ſight of that beauty he ſo much ador'd, was return'd to <hi>Salamanca;</hi> where being advertiz'd by Letters, of this nights ſtrange ſucceſſe, he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170135:16"/>wrote immediately to <hi>Albanius,</hi> recom mending to him, with ſuch endearing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as would have mov'd a Spirit leſſe tender than his to have obſerv'd his deſires, the Care of his Daughter; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him ſuch a large teſtimony of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality for what he had already done, as might well declare the generoſity of his minde, and the plentifulneſſe of his eſtate. At length, ſome emergent occaſions cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him away into <hi>Italy,</hi> he enjoyned an intimate Friend, to be nigh in vigilance and care, to the bringing up of his Daughter; ſtill giving ſo liberally, upon all occaſions, that in a ſhort ſpace <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> became very rich, and had where withal to live contentedly, and at eaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> (for ſo the yong diſguiſed Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſe was call'd) grew up in beauty, as in years, every day adding to her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: no ſooner had ſhe attain'd to thoſe years that made her capable of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, but ſhe was courted by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal men of the Village, who with Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, though Ruſtick lays, ambition'd to be her Servants. She was ſo fair, that the Snow, which (if it had ſtay'd in the middle Region, would have been accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted white) compar'd with her Skin, quire
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170135:16"/>loſt it's reputation; her Hair was of a hue, only ſo remore from the Sun, and ſo neer reſembling the Earth, as, leſt being all of Gold, it ſhould have been ſnatch'd up to it's own proper Sphere, and ſo have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſecond <hi>Ariadne</hi>'s Crown; her Eyes, though black, yet quick and vivaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſo watchful over their own glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they were ſcarce permitted a lawful liberty; her Cheeks free from the leaſt tincture of art, diſplay'd ſuch a purely mingled white and purple, that they could not, without diſparagement, have been compared either to Ivory or Gilloflowers; her Mouth was like a little Wound, and her Lips animated Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal, through whoſe tranſparency the blood diſcover'd it's pure redneſſe; her Hands, two white ſoft Lilies, but much whiter and ſofter than any the earth bears; or at leaſt, they had been certainly taken for Snow, but that they were unmelted by the Sun: ſhe was of a Diſpoſition mild and complaiſant, yet of ſo natural a courtly behaviour, that it might be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd how in ſo low a condition ſhe could bear ſo enlarged a Soul, ſhe was much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the gallantry of ſome Gentlemen that us'd to paſſe that way, and was much in their company, not out
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170135:17"/>of any wanton deſires, but out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that well became her; and ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betray'd the Illuſtriouſneſſe of her birth. (So hard it is for thoſe deſcended from a generous Lineage not to diſcover thoſe vertuous inclinations that are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary to them.) She was walking forth one Summer-night, to cool her ſelf with the freſh Evening-gale, and to delight her ſelf with the ſweet ſmels of Flowers, which the officious Airs brought to her on their wings, to pleaſe her; when there hapned to paſſe by a Gentleman of <hi>Madrid</hi> who was call'd <hi>Don Franciſco Oſorio,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with many Friends and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; who caſt his Eyes upon her; and though ſhe was clad in mean attire, was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd at the unexpected ſight of ſo ſurpaſſing a beauty, whereby ſhe was fancy'd to him to be ſome rural Deity: forward he paſs'd; and although he could have found in his heart a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times to have look'd back upon her, yet he abſtain'd, when he conſider'd with himſelf that it would have been a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to him, if he ſhould be ſeen to be overcome with her beauty, who was the inhabitant of a poor Village: as if a Diamond were of the leſſe price, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inchas'd in Lead, or circled about
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170135:17"/>with counterfeit Stones. His Reaſon at length aſſiſting him to overcome the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Will, he went on his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and arriv'd at <hi>Aranjuez;</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſpatch'd the buſineſſe he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, with the greateſt expedition that could be imagin'd, he ſo order'd his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Madrid,</hi> as to ſtay a while by the way at <hi>Pinto;</hi> (for there is a mans King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where his Deſire keeps Court;) his intent was to ſee <hi>Silvia,</hi> and to bring his companions to a ſight of her, that they might be Judges whether he had not a ſufficient pretence for his ſtaying there: they inform'd themſelves from a certain labouring-man (whom they had won to their Service with Gifts) that ſhe was walking in a Garden, with ſome other Virgins her companions.</p>
            <p>It was about the time that the Sun ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcur'd by a very dusky evening, was juſt taking his leave of the day, when they all going to ſee her, met her coming forth of the Garden; <hi>Don Oſorio</hi> began to ſalute her with a reſpect greater than her ſeeming quality requir'd: And ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king advantage of the darkneſſe of the night, he ſpake ſome things as a prelude to the diſcovery of his Paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia,</hi> although well pleas'd that ſhe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170135:18"/>was courted by a perſon of that quality and behaviour, was yet very ſlow to make any Anſwers, for fear ſhe ſhould be judged to diſcover ſomthing of lightneſſe in them, or at leaſt, want of wit: for where there is a diſparity of conditions between perſons, there cannot ſafely be an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate familiarity; the ſoundeſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſteſt of their intentions being apt to be made the worſt of, and diſcountenanc'd. At length, overcome with a Maidenly ſhamefac'dneſſe, ſhe made more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary haſte to be gone, partly out of her own modeſt inclinations, partly that ſhe might take away all occaſions from her companions of inſulting over her fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that they might not think that ſhe had leſſe command over her Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons than they. <hi>Don oſorio</hi> in the mean while was lefe differently affected, contented that he had obtain'd the ſight of her whom he ador'd; grieved to be ſo ſoon deprived of ſuch a happineſſe: but conſidering with himſelf, that this disfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour might rather ariſe from the power of her baſhfulneſſe, than from any contempt of his perſon, he reſolv'd to try whether he could, with leſſe open teſtimonies of his Service, move her to be more ſenſible toward him; he went out in the depth of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170135:18"/>night, with certain muſical Inſtruments, the choiceſt his love and curioſity could ſearch out; and leaning to the Wall of <hi>Silvia</hi>'s little habitation, he began three Canzonets; praiſing, among other things, the perfections of her Face; the great beauty of her Mouth, which was ſuch, that it needed not the help of her Eye to ſubdue the heart of any man alive: which he ſung in Conſort with two other Muſicians, his Servants:</p>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>So looks the virgin-Roſe,</l>
               <l>Which cheriſh'd by the genial South;</l>
               <l>Her crimſon beauties doth diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>As do the ruby-portals of her Mouth:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which when ſhe doth unfold,</l>
               <l>Two bright tranſparent rows</l>
               <l>Of Pearly ye may behold;</l>
               <l>From between which a breath of amber flows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>AMore than <hi>Tyrian</hi> purple doth o'reſpread</l>
               <l>Her Lips, which ſofter are</l>
               <l>Than the Swans Down, and ſmoother far:</l>
               <l>The coſtly Juyce that dwells</l>
               <l>In Oriental ſhells,</l>
               <l>To them looks pale, they are ſo purely red.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170135:19"/>
Fair Cheeks, that look like bluſhing Roſes plac'd</l>
               <l>In pureſt Ivorie;</l>
               <l>Or Coral within Snow inchas'd:</l>
               <l>The glories of the Spring</l>
               <l>Grow pale, and languiſhing</l>
               <l>For Envie, ſo cutſhin'd by them to be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>SWeetly triumphing Eyes,</l>
               <l>That in two cryſtal Priſons do contain</l>
               <l>Death in a frowns diſguiſe:</l>
               <l>How gladly would I die, to be by theſe eyes ſlain!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Delightful cruelty</l>
               <l>Of thoſe all-charming Eyes,</l>
               <l>That have on me, deſign'd to try</l>
               <l>With what a pleaſing Empire they can tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> diligently liſt'ning to this Song, knew that it was ſung by the Gentleman who had talked with her the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; She was once about to have op'ned the Window, to teſtifie her grateful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment of his civility, and that it might appear her behaviour was not ſo ruſtick as her habit; but fearful, that if ſhe ſhould have been ſeen, it might have render'd her the object of ſome malicious tongue
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170135:19"/>that would perhaps have taken that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of bringing her Honour in queſtion, ſhe held it fitter to forbear. There were in <hi>Don Franciſco</hi> thoſe Excellencies, that ſhe could not chuſe but be much taken with his comely proportion of Body, his courteſie, and his diſcreet carriage: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the good opinion which his merit gain'd him in her heart, there ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven'd a certain natural inclination, which ſprung from the agreeableneſſe of their humours: but being dejected at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of her mean parentage, ſhe could not perſwade her ſelf that his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications were real; and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to ſtifle in the birth this new-ſprung Affection, which notwithſtanding had already taken too deep an impreſſion to be eaſily effac'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Oſorio,</hi> on the other ſide, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded himſelf diſeſteem'd, becauſe he thought ſhe had ſlighted the Praiſes he had beſtowed on her in his Serenade; not comprehending, that out of a prudent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'dneſſe ſhe had diſſembled her true ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions: So that he return'd to his Lodging in greater diſquiet of minde than (one would have thought) the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Judgment would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: he imploy'd all the powers of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170135:20"/>his minde to fortifie himſelf againſt her diſdain, and to enable him to overcome the violence of his paſſion; but he ſtrove againſt the ſtream: The likelieſt way he had, was, to remove from that place, wherein to have tarried, would have been to have proclaim'd himſelf her Lover; and to make that courſe, whereby he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to manifeſt his Service, a means to diſoblige her; for he could not but be ſenſible that the habit he appear'd in at that time, would prove diſadvantageous to him in his Addreſſes to <hi>Silvia,</hi> which thereby became liable to a ſtrict obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſuch an obſcure Village.</p>
            <p>Once he had in his minde to returne to <hi>Madrid;</hi> but to that, the force of love, and <hi>Silva</hi>'s beauty, would by no means conſent. In this languiſhing and deſperate condition, for a while, remain'd the enamour'd <hi>Oſorio,</hi> reſtleſſe in his minde, and toſt to and fro between many contrary imaginations: At laſt he advis'd with himſelf, (and reſolv'd to put it to a tryal) whether if he ſhould diſguize him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and change his habit, he might not become more acceptable to her; ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that it might be, perhaps, not ſo much the diſlike of his perſon, as the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd diſparity of eſtate, that might make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170135:20"/>her backward to impart her Favours to him (for it is not ſafe to give way to the deſiring of that, of which there is little hope of ever attaining to) but thought that if <hi>Silvia</hi> ſhould behold him deveſted of his true quality, and clad in mean Country-attire, ſhe might haply ſhew leſſe averſion to him, deſcending to be her equal, than ſhe did before.</p>
            <p>In this Reſolution he ſlept, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to leave no way unattempted, to calm the inquietude of his thoughts. On the morrow, he call'd to him the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the houſe, to whom he diſclos'd the Love he had for <hi>Silvia,</hi> and the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wherewith ſhe had hitherto treated him, in lieu of all the diligent tenders of his Service: And withal, reveal'd to him the deſign which he had pitch'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the ſubduing of her impaſſible heart; deſiring him to add his beſt advice and aſſiſtance for the furtherance of this his purpoſe; for which he promis'd ſuch a large reward, that he ſhould be the better for it while he liv'd. This he urged ſo paſſionately, and with ſuch tender ſighs, that the Old-man, partly oblig'd with his promiſes, partly affected with the ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of his condition, faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, that on his part there ſhould be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170135:21"/>nothing omitted that might conduce to his advantage; and calling to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance a Son of his, who, when he left his Country, was ſcarce arriv'd to the Spring of his Age, of whom he had not heard any News, ſince his departure, till that very day: He told him, <q>He would give out that his Son was newly arriv'd home, and that he might very oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely make uſe of this pretence to bring his wiſhed deſign to effect.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Franciſco</hi> exceedingly pleas'd, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd the Old-man, and gave him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thanks for his happy invention; and imparting to his Companions the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his diſguize, he went for a while to <hi>Madrid,</hi> where fitting himſelf with Cloaths for the purpoſe, very near, though of the plain Country-faſhion, and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Name from <hi>Don Franciſco</hi> to <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denio;</hi> he return'd one night to the houſe of his new Father, who, againſt his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, had divulg'd throughout all the neighbourhood the return of his own long look'd-for Son. All the Friends and Neighbours came to ſee him, and gave him a thouſand welcoms home. Every one glad to ſee him ſo well improv'd, and become ſo brave a man through the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of his Travels.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170135:21"/>
               <hi>Cardenio</hi> began to be acquainted with the principal men of the place: he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well the bounds of Courteſie, and what gallantry the meanneſſe of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guize would give him leave to uſe; ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hav'd himſelf toward all, that he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd of all, and yet attracted the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will of all. Thus liv'd he joyful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the happy ſucceſſe of his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize; and underwent with a great deal of willingneſſe this homely kinde of life; for he had every day happy opportunities offer'd of ſeeing <hi>Silvia:</hi> he ſerv'd her warily, and with much zeal; taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his being newly come home, to viſit her often; which gave occaſion to ſome curious pryers into other mens acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (with which ſort of people all places abound) to ſay that <hi>Cardenio</hi> lov'd <hi>Silvia;</hi> that his love was betray'd by his very eyes, which could not diſſemble; and his following her from place to place, as if he had been the ſhadow of her brightneſſe. She well obſerv'd the notice that was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and therefore carried her ſelf with the greater Caution; not that it was any new thing to her to be Courted, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe thought there was not any, anong all the Country-Swains, more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving her Favour, than <hi>Cardenio.</hi> She
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170135:22"/>being of a moſt prompt and acute wit, could eaſily diſcern the Graces and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of him that ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſerve her; and having well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the admirable Attraits of this her new Servant, ſhe could not chuſe but think him worthy of her Love. (It is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that that thing ſhould ever be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely diſpleaſing, which hath once throughly pleas'd.) So that by little and little ſhe remitted much of her natural ſeverity; diſcovering her minde fo far, as it might plainly appear, That if ſhe lov'd not, ſhe at leaſt was pleas'd with his Service; which came to the ſame paſſe: for whoſoever begins to be pleas'd with any thing, takes no pleaſure in deſpiſing it.</p>
            <p>She looks now upon <hi>Cardenio</hi> as on her equal; ſaw her ſelf lov'd by him, and envy'd by many of the yong Shepherdeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes her Companions, who us'd in her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence oft-times to load <hi>Cardenio</hi> with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite praiſes; therefore ſhe thought ſhe ſhould have been guilty of a grievous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, ſhould ſhe have perſecuted with diſdain one that dy'd for her. Many times would <hi>Silvia</hi> admit theſe conſiderations to her minde, in reſpect of many who had formerly ſerv'd her. Seldome doth a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170135:22"/>Woman lay to heart the ſufferings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, until ſhe have undergone the pangs of Love her ſelf: now <hi>Silvia</hi> loves; and ſince ſhe loves, obligeth <hi>Cardenio</hi> with many Favours. As ſhe ſtood alone one night in her Chamber, revolving theſe things in her minde, and Contemplating the perfections of the feigned Shepherd; Her Old-father (for ſo <hi>Albanius</hi> had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been reputed by her) being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of the Addreſſes that many had made to her to obtain her Affection, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <hi>Cardenio,</hi> whom he judg'd the ſame that he feign'd himſelf to be; and fearing leſt ſhe ſhould unadviſedly run into ſome misbeſeeming action, or engage her ſelf in a Match that would be inferiour to the nobleneſſe of her deſcent; He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to her the ſtory of her Parents miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, and the ſtrange accidents of her Birth, which brought her into this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; And ſhewing her ſome of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which he had receiv'd from her true Father, aſſur'd her, that ſhe ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, ſooner than ſhe imagin'd, to a far more ſplendid manner of living than at preſent ſhe enjoy'd; that it behov'd her to bethink her ſelf, and conſider that the Actions of great perſons are more ſtrictly cenſur'd, than thoſe of the meaner ſort:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170135:23"/>And that ſince ſhe was born with ſuch great Endowments of Wit and Beauty, and above all, ſuch vertuous and diſcreet inclinations, he beſought her not to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any demeanour that might in the leaſt wiſe diſhonour the generous Blood of which ſhe was ſprung; nor to hearken unto the Sollicitations of every fooliſh admirer of her, ſince none, thereabouts, could come neer to deſerve her.</p>
            <p>With notable attention did the diſcreet Maid hear the ſage Counſel of <hi>Albanius,</hi> and the Secret of her Nativity; ſhe gave full Credit to all that he had related, and promis'd not to ſwerve from his Advice; remaining not leſſe troubled in her minde, than undeceiv'd in her own eſteem: the thoughts of <hi>Cardenio</hi> 's deſerts, came of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into her minde, and the inequality of their eſtates, which ſtrictly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to with-hold all her former Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours from him; which her minde could not very eaſily conſent unto: yet conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, That to love him was to diſpleaſe <hi>Albanius,</hi> and ſtain the greatneſſe of her Birth, ſhe reſolv'd with her ſelf (although not without much regret) to forget that ever ſhe had the leaſt appearance of love toward him, and to expect that day wherein her Affections ſhould meet with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170135:23"/>a ſubject agreeable to her quality. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denio,</hi> upon a calm evening, looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Walls of <hi>Albanius</hi> his Palace, (for ſo of a Cottage the preſence of <hi>Silvia</hi> had made it, in his eſteem) he ſaw her come forth, directing her walk towards a green flouriſhing Meadow, to paſſe away with pleaſure the tedious night, and to enjoy the benefit of thoſe cool Airs that gave life to the ſweet Flowers in that cheerful ſeaſon. <hi>Cardenio</hi> following, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd her unawares; but in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that he might be perceiv'd to have done it rather out of deſign than chance: Notwithſtanding, this diſguized <hi>Diana</hi> kept on her pace toward the place inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; ſhe ſeated her ſelf in a little Garden of Common Flowers, which Nature, without the help of humane induſtry, had produc'd, aſſiſted by a murmuring Rivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let that ran hard by; and ſeriouſly revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in her minde that which <hi>Albanius</hi> had the night before related to her, not without much admiration at the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it; ſhe began to bewaile her miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap; for that no ſooner had ſhe almoſt yielded up her Affections to a Gentleman, whom for his Merits and his true Love to her, ſhe could not chuſe but very much eſteem, but ſhe was taken off by an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170135:24"/>of being far inferiour to him in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: and now that <hi>Cardenio</hi> being thought her equal, had ſo far ſucceeded in his Service toward her, as to be thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of anſwerable Love and Reſpect, the late knowledg ſhe had learn'd of her noble Deſcent, interpos'd as an obſtacle to their happineſſe, and forbids them any farther progreſſe. Theſe thoughts drave her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch an extaſie, and fixt <hi>Cardenio</hi> ſo deeply in her minde, that her outward ſence had not leiſure to take notice of him, though ſtanding at a ſmall diſtance from her: He on the other ſide perceiving the diſturbance of her thoughts, was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reveal the Secrets of his heart ſome other way, than by directing his ſpeech to her herſelf. So taking on him not to have ſeen her, and giving truce a while to his reſtleſſe thoughts, he breath'd forth this ſweet amorous Sonnet.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>HIther I come, delightful Groves,</l>
               <l>To ſpend my ſighs, and make my moan;</l>
               <l>To whoſe ſtill ſhades it beſt behoves</l>
               <l>To make my plaints and ſorrows known:</l>
               <l>And the gentle Trees invite</l>
               <l>To pity my diſcons' late plight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170135:24"/>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>'Tis rigorous love that doth torment</l>
               <l>This diſturbed heart of mine,</l>
               <l>But of a Creature ſo divine,</l>
               <l>That I ought not to repent</l>
               <l>To have lov'd, though unlov'd again;</l>
               <l>The ſole Author of my pain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Is bright <hi>Silvia,</hi> gentle Bow'rs,</l>
               <l>To your gloomy walks unknown?</l>
               <l>Who loves to ſpend the harmleſſe hours</l>
               <l>Among ſilent Groves alone:</l>
               <l>And can with her preſence bright,</l>
               <l>To the darkeſt ſhades give light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Silvia</hi> hath about her, Charms,</l>
               <l>Nations able to ſubdue:</l>
               <l>And can conquer with thoſe Arms</l>
               <l>More than mightieſt Kings can do.</l>
               <l>But I that am her chiefeſt aim,</l>
               <l>Am deſtin'd to the greateſt flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170135:25"/>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>I die, <hi>Silvia,</hi> when I behold</l>
               <l>Thoſe Eyes that ſet on fire my heart;</l>
               <l>Yet I (for love is uncontrol'd)</l>
               <l>Greedy and fond of my own ſmart,</l>
               <l>And Captive to my miſery,</l>
               <l>Love to behold thoſe ſtars, and die.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>So paſſionately was this ſung by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denio,</hi> and ſo deep an impreſſion took it, in the heart of <hi>Silvia,</hi> that ſhe reſolved with her ſelf not to return home, until ſhe had had ſome diſcourſe with the Author of thoſe melodious complaints. <hi>Cardenio</hi> came forward, and ſeem'd to be ſurpriz'd himſelf with the ſuddenneſſe of meeting her in that place: ſhe at firſt drew back, as intending to behave her ſelf toward him in a more reſerv'd manner than ſhe had done before <hi>Albanius</hi> inform'd her of her true Condition; but ſhe was ſhaken in her reſolution, when ſhe ſaw him repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her more full of Charms at that time, than ever; and ſo much the more, by how much the leſſe poſſibility ſhe ſaw of enjoying him: however, unavoidably they being met, ſhe enquir'd of him (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170135:25"/>though ſhe knew full well, that it was he himſelf, who had lately been the <hi>Orpheus</hi> of thoſe Woods, and that this Song was directed to her, having heard her name more than once repeated in it, and could willingly have been contented to have heard it many times iterated in ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-mournful a Song) whether it were he that had but even now ſo pathetically re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the Woods his amorous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints? He anſwer'd, that it was; and that the ſorrows which he ſuſtain'd through the cruelty of her whom he ſerv'd, had forc'd him to expreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in that manner: Upon which words, <hi>Silvia</hi> offer'd to be gone, fearing to hear that which might cauſe a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Vermilion to riſe in her Cheeks, and ſo intangle her ſelf more deeply in that from which ſhe ſought to flie: <hi>Cardenio</hi> with little ado detain'd her, aſſuring her that if ſhe would but be pleas'd to hear what he had at preſent to ſay, it ſhould be the utmoſt limit of her Favour that he would aſpire to; and having obtain'd her Conſent, he began in this manner: <q>Had I thought, <hi>Silvia,</hi> that my Love would have offended you, either as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a diſparagement, or any other way diſtaſteful to you; Heaven knows, I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170135:26"/>would ſooner with my own hands have ended this wretched life, than not to have put an end to the occaſion of your diſpleaſure: but preſuming upon the confidence of a paſſion the moſt pure and innocent in the world, I did imagine that the diſcovery of it could not be capable to offend you: yet hitherto I have only taken the boldneſſe to diſcharge my breſt of thoſe reſtleſſe thoughts that incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred it, only by communicating them to the friendly ſecret of theſe Trees, who I was ſure would not divulge ought committed to their truſt: Here I ſtood, as you ſee, ſinging and bewailing (two things alike incident to thoſe that Love) and I conjecture that I have been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard by you; therefore ſince I am diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, let it not, I beſeech you, trouble you, but conſider how eaſily you may ſuſtain the tediouſneſſe of being belov'd, ſince I can paſſe through the torment of loving. That you will love me, <hi>Silvia,</hi> is a thing I dare not require; but beg of you, that you will not take it amiſs that you are lov'd by me: For alas! my love is of ſo ſmall a value, that I have ſcarce courage enough to perſwade my ſelf that I love you: and I ſhall comfort my ſelf with this conſideration, That if
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170135:26"/>my love ſhall want the ſatisfaction of your Returns, it may at leaſt be thought the more perfect, by continuing fervent without the hopes of recompence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi>'s heart, formerly hardened with diſdain, is now melted into pity by the moving Speech of <hi>Cardenio:</hi> fain ſhe would have been gone, but had not power to go; but aſſiſted with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of no ordinary Woman, ſhe put on a gallant reſolution, and parted, with this rigorous Anſwer, <q>That he could have done no more, if he had plainly told her, That he hated her.</q> No ſooner was ſhe gone, but ſhe was ready to weep that ſhe had left him; griev'd that ſhe muſt flie from him, whom, of all the world, ſhe moſt affected; and ſory that ſhe had not been kept ignorant of the nobleneſſe of her Family. <q>Ah <hi>Cardenio</hi> (ſaid ſhe, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes looking back) how willingly would I pay thee back the reſpect thou beareſt me, were it not for blemiſhing the greatneſſe of my Birth! O that I could obtain of Heaven, to ennoble thee with a Condition equal to my ſelf! how willingly ſhould I then ſacrifice unto thee a heart, that is now ſcarce my own?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Complaints had meaſur'd out a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170135:27"/>pretty diſtance of way from him, but with ſuch regret, that ſhe was like to have made ſo bold with her modeſty, as to have return'd back to hearten him whom ſhe left ſo diſconſolate, with the evidence of more preſent Love, though ſmaller hopes of Love for the ſuture. <hi>Cardenio,</hi> on the other ſide, would not turn back after her, for fear of adding to her diſcontent, thinking ſhe had been indeed throughly diſpleas'd: his prudence made him diſtruſtful; and by how much the more he lov'd, by ſo much the more he fear'd; and by how much the more he fear'd, ſo much the more he blinded himſelf with the opinion of <hi>Silvia</hi>'s disfavour: but that which aggravated his hard hap the more, was, to conſider, That the diſguiſing his quality, did no whit avail to the altering of her reſolution; for when he appear'd in his right ſhape, a true Gentleman, ſhe was altogether averſe: and now that he had put on the Habit of a Country-Swain, ſhe was as much offended, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he could have been contented for her ſake, to had led his life perpetually in that obſcure Equipage; and would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have renounc'd the greatneſſe of his Birth, that he might have enjoy'd his adored <hi>Silvìa.</hi> But to comfort him a little
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170135:27"/>in theſe diſaſters, he met with an object ſomwhat ſympathizing with his own Condition; for obſerving the Trees which grew thereabout, among the reſt, he chanc'd to caſt his Eye upon one, of ſo ruſſet a hue, and ſo naked of Leaves, that it appear'd among the other Trees like one in diſgrace, and as if Winter, baniſh'd from all the world beſide, had there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up her habitation. Seeing therefore he had lighted upon ſo fit a Companion of his Afflictions, with whom to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate his griefs, he regardleſſe, ſung his misfortunes in this manner.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>UNhappie Tree, who in thy greener years,</l>
               <l>Haſt ſtood the ſhook of many a winters rage;</l>
               <l>Now thou art free from either hopes or fears</l>
               <l>Of ſadder Fates to come, or theſe t' aſſwage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Thou might'ſt have been the glory of this place,</l>
               <l>Had not the rigour of untimely Fate</l>
               <l>Rob'd thy fair Branches of their verdant grace,</l>
               <l>And thee reduc'd to this deſpis'd eſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170135:28"/>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou haſt outliv'd thy hopes, which are expir'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I linger out, and languiſh in deſpair:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Joys are paſt, and therefore not deſir'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But I the preſent ſcoffs of Fortune bear.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>How willingly in this calamitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yield I to act my ſelf the chiefeſt part!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And yet I have a kinde of fear to die;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As loth to be remov'd from this ſweet ſmart.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>To thee, that ſeaſon which on every thing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Except thee, ſmiles, is cruel and unkind;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To me that cruel fair, who is my ſpring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More rigid is than the bleak</hi> Scythian <hi>wind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or Winters rugged blaſts: yet do not I</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Think ſtrange, ſince to be cruel, is her property.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>In the midſt of theſe harmonious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, the night ſtole on, and <hi>Silvia</hi> with ſtedfaſt attention ſtood all this while at her window, watching to ſee if <hi>Cardenio</hi> would appear; which he did not, till
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170135:28"/>having retir'd himſelf to his Chamber, he had chang'd his Country-Habit, and inſtead thereof, put on the moſt rich and ſplendid Garment of all thoſe he brought along with him, in reſerence to whatever occaſion might emerge: thus attir'd he came, when all others were buried in night and ſilence, toward the Manſion of his cruel <hi>Silvia;</hi> who, what with the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the ſeaſons heat, and the reſtleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her thoughts, could not prevail with ſleep to take poſſeſſion of her eyes, that ſo her minde might for a while have been diverted from thoſe cares wherein it was involv'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardenio</hi> drew near, reſolving to try a ſecond change, to ſee if the altering his Apparel for the better, would bring the like alteration to his Fortune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> all this while was ſtanding at her window; and ſeeing him on a ſudden not to come forward, until he had by a ſign fignified his deſire to ſpeak; She ſtreight conſulted with her honour how ſhe were beſt to demean her ſelf toward his requeſt with the ſafety of her modeſty and civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: which that ſhe might the more ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliberate, ſhe was about to have ſhut the Caſement, but was prevented by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denio,</hi> who beſought her not fear that a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170135:29"/>few words from him (her attention to which, would be but little loſſe of time) could have power to convert her from that obdurate rigour wherein ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to perſiſt: and without expecting her Anſwer, that he might not let ſlip the occaſion which offer'd it ſelf, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his Speech in this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>fair Shepherdeſs, a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who not leng ſince paſsing through this place, chanc'd to eſpy that excellent beauty of yours, which made you in my Opinion, ſcarce deſcend to be a mortal Woman. But I would I had been born without eyes, that I might have been excus'd from the ſight of that beauty which hath roh'd me of my repoſe, and the ſerenity of my life: my greateſt unhappineſſe was, for that having once ſeen you, I was preſs'd with an eager deſire of ſeeing you again; for what greater misfortune can there be, than by a fatal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to chain ones Affection to a perſon, who returns nothing but Coldneſſe and Diſdain? returning back to gaze on thoſe Eyes which were the ſource of my Afflictions, I found out a means, with much ado, to come to your ſight and ſpeech; but I was entertain'd with ſuch a frozen indifferency, that my deſpair was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bounds or reſpite; yet I endeavour'd to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the impetuoſity of my flames, by frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the delightful divertiſements of the Court;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170135:29"/>and I had ſurely done it, had you been leſs fair, or that fairneſs leſs predominant over my ſoul: but finding it impoſsible, ever to forget the charms of thoſe fatal looks which have inthral'd my reaſon and my quiet with indiſſolvable fetters; I could not be at reſt till I returned to the place where I loſt my Liberty, intending to make tryal whether I might not be ſo much the better accepted, by how much the more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and with the greater obſervance I applied myſelf to your compaſsion; putting my ſelf in hope, that if I did not finde love, I ſhould at leaſt finde a favourable reſpect toward the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of ſo devoted a heart. And now I attend the doom that I muſt truſt to, from your own mouth; and however it prove, whether contrary to what I exſect, or not, it will yet be pleaſure to me, to be convinc'd that I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd to become yours, although I have not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited to have the Honour to own you for mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> hearkned the more attentively, to ſee if by the liſtning to the words of her ſeeming new Servant, ſhe could forget <hi>Cardenio</hi> fancy'd in his old ſhape: But as it oft hapneth, that a Lover takes a ſpecial liking to the very actions of the perſon lov'd; ſo ſhe calling to remembrance the manner of his garb as ſhe fancy'd it in his other habit, would needs diſlike the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs he made in this; as if the alteration
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170135:30"/>of his Attire, had chang'd the Faſhion of his Voice or Action. 'Tis ſtrange to ſee how humorous the paſſions of Lovers are: <hi>Cardenio</hi> is he, who the night before parlied with her, and was inwardly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; and the ſelf-ſame <hi>Cardenio,</hi> but even now, a Supplieant at her Feet, and is rejected: then a Villager, and meanly clad; now a Gentleman, &amp; having on ſuch Apparel as well beſeem'd him that might preſume to be her Servant. Who would have thought, that ſhe ſhould now diſlike him, when ſhe had neither his unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor any other crime to object againſt him? Miraculous is the myſtery of Love; wherein nothing, be it never ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, is liked in a perſon disfavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but in a lov'd object, all Errors are diſpens'd with. When he was plain <hi>Cardenio,</hi> the homely Weeds he went in, rob'd him of his Gentility, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of her Favour: and now that his rich Attire diſcovered him a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and one deſerving her Affection; the cauſe of his diſ-eſteem was, that he ſeem'd transform'd from <hi>Cardenio</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man: and this ſeeming alteration in him, had a greater aſcendent upon her minde, than one would have thought poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; ſo that in fine, making that the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170135:30"/>cauſe of her diſguſt, which ought to have been her chiefeſt ſatisfaction, ſhe gave him this reſolute Anſwer, That <hi>he need not trouble himſelf any further about her; for that, beſides the diſproportion of his Eſtate to hers, he was to conſider the nature of the place; in which, being but a ſmall Village, curioſity and ſlanderous tongues abounded; every action, though with never ſo much integrity done, would be liable to the groſſeſt cenſure, and the effects of honeſt Love imputed to laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: but that which moſt of all debar'd him of all hopes of enjoying her, was, that ſhe had already parted with the right of diſpoſing of her own affections, which ſhe had long ſince engaged; and, that two ſeveral Loves ought not to harbour in one honeſt breſt: therefore ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd him to pardon her; and that if he lov'd her ſo truely as he profeſs'd, he would ſhew it by not coming again into thoſe places where ſhe us'd to be, leſt is ſhould be taken notice of, to the calling her Fame in queſtion:</hi> and ſo bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him farewel, ſhe ſhut the Window. <hi>Cardenio</hi> remain'd ſo bitterly ſtung with this cruel Reply, that he began almoſt to wiſh, that he had receiv'd his doom ſooner, that he might by this time have made an end of dying; thinking it more tolerable than his preſent ſtate; wherein, having ſo long lingred out his life in falſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170135:31"/>hopes, he was now to begin to die; he griev'd, not onely that ſhe was ſo averſe from loving him, but that the pawning of her affections to another, was the cauſe ſhe treated him ſo rigorouſly; and, as if his rich Habit had been the ſole cauſe of his Grievances, he tore it to pieces, reſolving to do penance in Rags for his Offences, although committed through error: he curs'd his evil Fortune, and wiſh'd ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to be disburthen'd of his wretched life, ſince in a manner he was already ſlain by the cruelty of <hi>Silvia,</hi> that he liv'd but to the ſence of his Miſeries, but was dead to all hopes: and ſeeing, that all the ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to her pity were ſhut againſt him, that to all his Prayers ſhe was a Rock, becauſe ſhe was uncivil and void of courteſie, not to be pleas'd with the moſt obſequious Services, becauſe ſhe took a pride in being ungrateful; with bravery of Apparel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, as wanting courtly breeding; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing a homely garb, out of high-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; denying her heart to him, whoſe faith &amp; conſtancy gave him a juſt preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to it, becauſe ſhe pretended that it was elſe where beſtowed: He bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that jealouſie hath oft-times wrought miracles in the moſt wavering &amp; obdurate minds, ſince a Woman is ever moſt apt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170135:31"/>to love being ſlighted, and to ſlight when ſhe is lov'd; and took on a reſolution, ſince his Truth and Simplicity ſo little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd, to betake himſelf to Subtilty, as his laſt Refuge; purpoſing to try if he could diſcover, who this fortunate Lover ſhould be, that deſerv'd to have the ſole poſſeſſion of <hi>Silvia</hi>'s heart: to effect which, an opportunity was ſoon offer'd. There dwelt in the Neighbourhood a young Shepherdeſs of a ſprightly air, gentily educated, rich, and not of the meaneſt Quality; ſhe having obſerv'd the compleatneſs of <hi>Cardenio,</hi> was many times ſo large in the Character of his worth, that it being reported to him, gave him ſufficient aſſurance, that it would have been no very hard matter for him to have obtain'd her Love: ſo that <hi>Cardenio</hi> began not obſcurely to declare himſelf her Lover. She, proud to be courted by him, counted her ſelf happy in being thought worthy of his obſervance.</p>
            <p>In his Letters he pretended much Love; but becauſe it was faigned, he manag'd his Expreſſions warily; and her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, though ſomewhat cunningly and coyly fram'd, were yet courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and far from giving him any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170135:32"/>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> in the mean time, who had been ſo ſevere to her ſelf, as to baniſh from her ſelf that perſon whom ſhe held ſo dear, purchas'd with the price of her health, the loſſe of that which ſhe eſteem'd more than her health; ſo really did ſhe love, ſo really did ſhe feign not to love; and was ſtrangely divided within her ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this one, yet divided, paſſion; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting whether it were beſt to adhere to her real Love, or to turn her feigned ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into real. When ſhe look'd upon her ſelf as Noble, ſhe could not endure to think of ſtaining her Honour with the mixture of an ignoble Blood: when ſhe look'd upon <hi>Cardenio</hi> as greatly meriting, ſhe thought it impoſſible to draw out her poor Pilgrimage of Life without him. In this plight, remain'd the unfortunately fair <hi>Silvia,</hi> wavering in her minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween not daring to love him, and not having the heart to reſolve to ſlight him; when ſuddenly, the unwelcome fame of her Lovers chang'd Affection arriv'd to her Ears; which ſtruck ſuch an amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into her heart, being careleſs of any other felicity than the enjoyment of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denio,</hi> (though but in imagination) that her life had like to have forſaken her, at the ſame inſtant that her jealouſie poſſeſs'd
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170135:32"/>her: one while ſhe intended to puniſh his neglect, by changing her love into hatred; but was not able to put in practice her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: for Love, although it be not eaſily produc'd without the conſent of our wills; yet being once ſprung up in the heart, and grown to maturity, it lieth not in our wills to remove it: another while, by coming where he might ſee her, to bring him to ſee his error; but that ſhe durſt not, leſt he profeſſing love to another, her reputation might have ſuffered by it: in fine, ſhe held it beſt to conceal, as much as ſhe could, thoſe torments, which the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of her jealouſie made her endure; although it would have been a great eaſe to her minde to have diſcovered them; whereas to keep them ſmother'd in her breſt, added much to the extremity of her anguiſh.</p>
            <p>One evening, a cool freſh gale of winde invited her to walk forth into the Fields; and the rather, as being deſirous to breath forth her grievances to thoſe quiet ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and to communicate her ſad thoughts to the pitiful Birds; wiſhing they were endued with articulate voice, that they might relate to <hi>Cardenio</hi> what ſhe ſuffer'd; when caſting her eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the skirts of a little Hill which ſerv'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170135:33"/>as a ſtately Crown to the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Plain, ſhe ſaw three men moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly ſet againſt the Life of one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; who notwithſtanding gallantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended himſelf; and recollecting all his Courage together, he made a ſhift, what with the puiſſance of his blows, and what with the advantage of place which he gain'd, and the skill where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he manag'd his Weapon, to keep off that approaching Fate wherewith the dangerouſneſſe of that aſſault threatned him: and to befriend him with her ſhades, the night came on ſo faſt, that, partly having the darkneſs of their fact repreſented before them through the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the nights darkneſs; partly being ſore wounded by the valour of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, they ſled away, leaving him as they thought dead, or with ſmall hopes of Life. <hi>Silvia</hi> came nigh, and ſaw claſped in the Arms of a fair Shepherdeſs, this undaunted Combatant; who welter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his own Blood, gave to underſtand by the ghaſtlineſſe of his look, that he wanted but little of yielding himſelf up to death. <hi>Silvia</hi> being about to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of them the reaſon of this tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal accident; firſt obſerving the Maid, well perceiv'd, that it was her Corrival,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170135:33"/>and the Author of her Jealouſies; and afterward, looking intently upon the wounded man, knew him to be her falſe Lover, her revolted <hi>Cardenio:</hi> ſo grievous was the ſight unto her, ſo deeply did it ſtrike her heart, that ſhe could almoſt have wiſh'd that his Soul would quite forſake its unfaithful Manſion, both that ſhe might be free from the pain of her tormenting Jealouſie; and that he might ceaſe to be, ſince he ceas'd to be conſtant; but leaving it to the will of Heaven, ſhe ſuppreſs'd her diſtemper as well as ſhe could, and condeſcended to ask the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of her quiet, what was the cauſe of that tragical miſchance? Who Anſwer'd with a troubled mind, and weeping, <q>That <hi>Cardenio,</hi> whom ſhe paſſionately lov'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all men, ſtanding by her under the ſhade of thoſe Trees, had been aſſaulted by a man more fortunate in Riches than well deſcended, who repining at the good ſucceſs of his love, being perhaps himſelf a Corrival, thought it a ſhame to ſuffer one that was a meer ſtranger in that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to go ſo much beyond him in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all men, and to be an obſtacle to him in the courſe of his Love; therefore he ſought all opportunities to work his miſchief; and this night he found a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170135:34"/>means to put in practice his curſed treachery: for ſeeing us walk forth to take the Air, he followed privately, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with two others, choſen for ſuch a villanous intent; and when we leaſt dream'd of any ſuch ſuperchery attending us, they all Three ſet upon him in that cruel manner; and, though I interpos'd my ſelf, to ſhield him from the fury of their Blows, have left his life in that danger, wherein ye ſee it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> diſſembling her ill reſentment of the injury done her, (although her heart was ready to burſt with ſorrow and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) advis'd the diſconſolate Maid, That it was neceſſary to have recourſe forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to Juſtice, to accuſe the Authors of that villany, and to demand ſatisfaction for ſo inſufferable a wrong, and to take ſome courſe for the dreſſing of his Wounds; remaining there in the mean while her ſelf alone, and yet accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with a thouſand ſad thoughts: on the one ſide, her jealous rage inſtigated her to wiſh his death, without whom ſhe could not live: on the other ſide, her love and compaſſion mov'd her to pity his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; her love prevailing more to make her heart tender, than her rage to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170135:34"/>
               <hi>Cardenio</hi> liſting up his eyes, beheld <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi> not far off; and ſeeing himſelf free from the embraces of her, for whoſe ſake he had undergone this bloody Adventure, began to thank the cruelty of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, thinking that <hi>Silvia</hi> was invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thither by pity; having forgotten, at leaſt in that moment of time, her natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſeverity: but when he remembred himſelf, that his Apoſtacy was known to her, how ſecret ſoever ſhe kept it, he then pray'd that his wounds might prove ſo mortal, as to cauſe his ſpeedy deliverance from his loath'd Life, and all thoſe Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that attended it: but ſeeing, that that great effuſion of blood from a wound in his head onely, his other parts being protected by a ſtiff Leather Jerkin, which he wore under his diſgune, avail'd not to free him from his miſetable Life ſo ſoon as he deſir'd, he vow'd to be aveng'd on thoſe Aſſaſſinates for leaving him alive; imputing it to their malicious intentions to procure his dying by degrees, that ſo he might linger out his Life in that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting diſquiet of minde, which aroſe from his being diſcover'd to <hi>Silvia;</hi> who, after ſhe was ſatisfied, that thoſe Vermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion ſtreams guſh'd onely from the wound in his head; and, that that was not ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170135:35"/>neither, as was imagin'd (although had it been leſs, ſuch was her Love and pity to him, it would deeply have pierc'd her heart) ſhe wip'd off with her hand ſome of the congeal'd Blood that ſtuck upon his Face; and binding up that part of the head from whence the Blood iſſued, with a linnen cloath, queſtion'd him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Adventure; telling him, <hi>She admir'd how having ſo fair a Creature by his ſide, he could poſsibly receive any harm, were the oppoſition never ſo great; and, that if ſhe had ſeen her Lover in the like danger, ſhe would have ſo beſtirr'd her ſelf, that his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhould either have left him without hurt, or firſt tried upon her the goodneſs of their Swords; which if they had ſheathed in her breſt, ſhe ſhould have eſteemed it rather a Favour than an Injury, ſince ſhe would have been freed thereby from becoming a ſpectator of her Lover's harm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was to <hi>Cardenio</hi> a thing both ſtrange and unexpected, that <hi>Silvia</hi> ſhould be ſenſible of his ſuffering; &amp; made him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle revive his languiſhing hopes, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Compaſſion is oft the Harbinger of Love; and, that there is no Love ſo ſure, as that which ſprings from pity and to confirm the Truth of his Perſwaſion, he repeated to her the ſame Story, which ſhe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170135:35"/>ſo lately receiv'd from the mouth of the amorous Shepherdeſſe; although it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe reſented by <hi>Silvia,</hi> being the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time told, than it was at firſt; the force of jealouſie being moſt impetuous, when it is firſt conceived; and her Spirit was ſomewhat the more pacified, after he had ſo ſolemnly proteſted, <hi>That he was not in love with the fair Shepherdeſs whom ſhe ſaw, nor had made her any other requital of the Affection ſhe conceived toward him, than by general demonſtrations of Civility.</hi> For ſhould he have profeſs'd to love her, it might perhaps have prov'd as much to his diſadvantage, as it redounded to his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit that he was belov'd by her; it hapning, that although many Women by how much the more they are diſdain'd, themore earneſtly they love; yet others quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the more they are ſlighted, the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they grow in their Affections. <hi>Silvia</hi> preceiving, that if ſhe ſhould not now at length diſcloſe her minde to <hi>Cardenio,</hi> it might urge him to go on in his new love; ſhe thought it beſt to make uſe of the time, while there was no Company to diſturb her; forcing her ſelf to a faign'd laughter, (for had tears been needful, it had been needleſs to faign) ſhe began in this maner:</p>
            <p>
               <q>I ſwear to you, <hi>Cardenio,</hi> I cannot but be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170135:36"/>mov'd to Laughter, as oft as I conſider how ſtrangely the Opinions of Men do vary and contradict themſelves, in a ſhort ſpace; and, that being naturally unfix'd in your reſolutions, &amp; born with unconſtant minds, ye can have the face to be always accuſing our Sex of that inconſtancy w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is proper to your ſelves only, haply ſome women may juſtly have been charg'd with inconſtancy; but ſtil there hath been found on your parts a ſufficient cauſe to incite them to it: ſo that this defect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth not from their own inſtability, but the provocations of Men. What blame can ſhe be obnoxious to, who, either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd in the point of Honour, or by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever miſcarriage elſe offended, toward a falſe Pretender of Service, ſhould ſtrive to forget all Reſpect intended to ſuch a Man? How finely had I been ſerv'd, had I, out of a fond credulity preſently ſubmitted to your faign'd Adoration? Or ſuppoſe ſome over-ſenſible Lady, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by the prevalency of her Love, and the extream importunity of her Lovers Tears, admits him to the higheſt place of her eſteem; and he having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd what he ſo earneſtly ſought for, makes himſelf abſolute Maſter of her Heart, till ſatisfied with the eaſie fruition
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170135:36"/>of her Favours, he grow weary of them, and fall in love with the next Beauty he meets; and, which is worſe, never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, till by making his perfidious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings apparent to her, he kills her with the ſenſe of her own unhappineſſe: I would fain know, <hi>Cardenio;</hi> may not this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be held excus'd, if ſhe prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant to him? It ſeems we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to ſuffer all vexations whatſoever at your hands, and not ſo much as offer to be reveng'd for them; and your ſelves not bound to be touch'd with the leaſt ſhame for thoſe injuries you do us: you think the advantage of Wit, which you arrogate to your ſelves above our Sex, was given you on purpoſe to delude us; and our leſſe Prudence belike is allow'd us, onely that we may be wiſe enough to bear with your failings: if not, tell me, I conjure you, by that Reſpect which you once ſeem'd to owe me, and by the Beauty of that Maid that loves you ſo intirely, and could ſo eaſily conſent to ſit, and look on, while you were in ſuch danger of being ſlain; How could you ſo eaſily forget thoſe paſſionate preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which you offered to me with ſo much zeal and devotion? Did you not call to minde, how a few dayes ſince, I
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170135:37"/>ſaw you pitifully complaining, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting to the woods, whether your real paſſions, or your forgeries, I know not? And afterwards, did you not with great aggravation of your griefs, urge how much you had indured for my ſake; and, that the Torments and reſtleſſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations of your Spirit, were all the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of my unkindeneſſe? Moreover, did you not make ſerious Proteſtations to me, That ſhould your life out-dure many Ages, it would never be within your power to deſiſt from loving me? How happens it, if this be true, (as you are conſcious to your ſelf it is, and theſe very Trees can witneſs it) That I found you even now incircled in the Arms of a new Miſtreſs, whoſe love you may high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prize, ſince it hath been valued at the dear rate of ſo much blood. Tell me, <hi>Cardenio,</hi> upon theſe terms, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence is to be repos'd in Men that profeſſe never ſo much Love and Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Or, what could you have done more, if after the higheſt demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I could have given you of my Love, you had been forſaken of me? Muſt you make ſuch haſte to diſcover to me the falſeneſſe of your Faith, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you had received the leaſt aſſurance
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170135:37"/>of a favourable reception from me? are you ſo ſoon tired with thoſe Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which you ſo lately vow'd ſhould never have an end? Perhaps you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt your ſelf at Court, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween to requeſt, and to grant, there is little or no interval, unleſs it be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the want of opportunity: or it may be you did imagine me to be ſome Woman light of behaviour; expecting, that I ſhould have rendred my ſelf up to your firſt deceits, (for I know not under what other title your words ſhould paſſe) or if you have not entertain'd altogether ſo ſiniſter a conceit of me, could you have found in your heart, (if, as it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I might, (although it hath hapned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) being ſurpriz'd with the charms of your perſon or minde, I had offered my ſelf up a Victim to your impoſtures) to charge me with any blame, had I ſought to right my ſelf for this injury, in publiſhing you to the world a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious, unthankful, and diſloyal Man? Be aſſur'd, <hi>Cardenio,</hi> that to offer any indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to Ladies of honour and eſteem, is unſafe; for as they are alwayes deeply affected with the ſenſe of receiv'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, ſo they are apt to retaliate them, with a ſeverity void of pity or modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170135:38"/>as for me, (ſince through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of my good fortune, I have evaded the ſnares of your falſe pretenſions, through which I might have ſuffered many inconveniences, and which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps might have beguil'd the credulity of many an innocent Maid) I ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to conſider, ſince you take your ſelf to be ſo diſcreet, that it behov'd you to have leſs confidence in your merits, and not to conceive you ſelf arriv'd to that perfection, as to be able to ſubdue the affections of every woman you have to deal with: there are many defects in you, which you your ſelf know not of, becauſe you look upon your ſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the mirrour of your own Fancy.</q>
            </p>
            <p>She ended her Diſcourſe with an action that ſignified much diſdain; but yet ſo gracefully ſhe did it, that <hi>Cardenio</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely charm'd with that which extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled him: yet his heart was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what lightned, to ſee that <hi>Silvia,</hi> although ſhe had not declar'd her love to him, (for the ſharpneſs of her expreſſions forbid him to hope a thing ſo much tending to his content and happineſs) yet had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to ſo large an expoſtulation with him; and the better to ſatisfie her
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170135:38"/>of his untainted fidelity towards her, and to let her underſtand, that ſhe had been the onely Author of his inconſtancy, he made her this Reply:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Upon what ground it is, <hi>Silvia,</hi> that you ſo confidently aver an Univerſal fickleneſs &amp; ingratitude to be in all men, I know not, unleſs becauſe I ſeem to you to be ſuch a one, you thence infer that all men are ſo. but Heaven knows, you maintain an Argument, very difficult to be prov'd. There are many things to be Diſputed, ere your Opinion will gain belief. It is true, I was ſeen by you making my Complaints, and relating my Grievances to theſe Woods; and how well am I repaid for being ſo obſervant, even to a kinde of deifying of you, I have now to my ſorrow underſtood: but that ever I had a thought to relinquiſh or forget my firſt Love, ſo firmly devoted to you; I muſt both needs deny it, nor is it a thing likely to have been, whatever your ſuſpitions may ſuggeſt into your mind; and I ſhall be very unhappy, until you ſhall become ſenſible how much this confidence hath hitherto deceived you: and I would to Heaven, fair <hi>Silvia,</hi> ſince both to you it ſeems ſo indifferent, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170135:39"/>to me it would have been a means whereby the reſtleſſe intranquillities of my minde might have been ſomwhat allay'd, that what you imagin'd had been true. You tell me, You are very glad, (and ſeem to applaud your own Prudence in it) that you conſented nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Credit nor to Love me, ſince you now perceive how ill requited you ſhould have been; and that you would have had juſt cauſe to repent you of your Favours. Ah injurious Woman! what juſt cauſe can you have to traduce the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of my Love in ſuch ſort as you do? Grant that I am inconſtant, ought you not in charity to judge that I do it for the beſt, leſt in caſe your inclination be plac'd elſewhere, you ſhould be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with my ſollicitations? I know, <hi>Silvia,</hi> that you love; I know that the pains of an amorous paſſion ſit heavy on your heart, and that from a very good Authority; for there be who heard it from your own mouth. Seems it then, ſo great a crime in me, to ſeek to allay the violence of my flames, and trifle away the tediouſneſs of time by the diverſion of a counterfeit Love? Since I am deny'd the ſatisfaction of your real Love, I cannot comprehend, how you ſhould be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170135:39"/>taken with ſuch a qualm of pity, for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Wound in my Head, having in the mean while the Heart to bring my Life into danger, with a thouſand more mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Wounds. Was it not enough, <hi>Silvia,</hi> that I lov'd you without being requited? Was it not enough, that I was rejected by you? but that your Cruelty muſt needs mock me with an imputation of inconſtancy; your ſelf in the mean time continuing inflexible to a Paſſion the moſt pure and conſtant that any heart could be capable of: conſider with your ſelf, how gloriouſly you have done, by compelling me to languiſh out my ſorrowful minutes in a diſpair, which nothing but my Death can terminate. Seeing therefore, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports ſo little with you, whether I love you or no, ſuffer me to try, if by being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to forget you, I can triumph over my own Memory.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> very diligently (though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſturb'd at what he ſaid) hearkned to <hi>Cardenio</hi>'s words; and going about to vindicate her ſelf from that inhumanity, which her ſevere Behaviour toward him had cauſed in him to apprehend in her, ſhe was interrupted by a ſudden refort of people thither, who hearing of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Accident, came to inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170135:40"/>of the certainty of it: drawing neer, and viewing the Wound, they were glad when they ſaw it was not mortal (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much retarding his Recovery, as the want of Blood) and returned back to the Village with him, where his miſhap was univerſally bewail'd; ſo well his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant &amp; civil demeanour had made him belov'd among them: nor could the Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and Envy of a few, who had neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Pity, Reaſon, or Civility, be able to remove that good Eſteem, ſo generally conceiv'd of him. His Weakneſs forc'd him to keep his Bed for ſome few dayes in which time, he was carefully and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly look'd to by <hi>Silvia;</hi> and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended with much Joy and Pleaſure, the many Favours which ſhe conferr'd upon him; for which, to ſhew himſelf thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and confirm them the more ſure unto him, he did that which he knew would be acceptable to her. He wrote un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Country-Maid, through whoſe means his Love had been for a while withdrawn from <hi>Silvia,</hi> telling her, <q>That for his part, he was in that place rather a Stranger than a Native; that although it were the place where his Infant-yeers were ſpent, yet long abſence had made him to become a Stranger; and that it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170135:40"/>was not convenient for him to do any thing that might diſoblige thoſe with whom he was to lead the remainder of his Life; for that, as he came thither on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſee his Friends, ſo he intended not there to continue.</q> In fine, with theſe and the like pretences he diſ-ingaged himſelf from her; giving her clearly to underſtand, that he meant no longer to apply himſelf to her in the way of love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> receiv'd much joy and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from this reſolution of <hi>Cardenio;</hi> and ſent by a Maid of the Houſe in whom ſhe repoſed truſt, to tell him, <q>That as ſoon as he found himſelf in a condition to come abroad, ſhe deſired to ſee him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many things to impart to him, which perhaps he would not be unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be made acquainted with.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardenio</hi> counted every Hour an Age, earneſtly expecting that happy Day, wherein he ſhould have the opportunity to diſcover his minde freely to her, and to prevail with her not to hold him in ſuſpence any longer. <hi>Silvia</hi> on the other ſide pray'd heartily for his amendment; being fully reſolv'd, at their next meeting, to treat him leſs diſdainfully and more obligingly than heretofore; for that now the Love of him had ſo abſolute an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170135:41"/>in her heart, that ſhe reſolv'd with her ſelf, in caſe her Parents ſhould oppoſe her choice, as thinking it a match too much beneath her, utterly to relinquiſh the Wealth and Grandeur of her own condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to live with him, though in the moſt obſcure equipage: ſince no advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or worldly intereſt had ſo powerful a conſideration with her, as her love of <hi>Cardenio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One night among the reſt, while the good old man, <hi>Albanius,</hi> having heard of the correſpondency between her and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denio,</hi> was beginning to reprove her, as if ſhe had not ſufficiently given credit to what he had made known to her concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her Quality; there came to the door a man, who inquired for <hi>Albanius,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That a Gentleman without deſired to ſpeak with him. Albanius</hi> went down; <hi>Silvia</hi> in the mean time muſing with her ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the reſolution ſhe had taken in the behalf of <hi>Cardenio:</hi> as he was going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Gate, to ſee who inquir'd for him, there met him a Lady of a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome proportion, and gentile preſence, whom more by ſigns than her words, he underſtood to be the Mother of <hi>Silvia;</hi> who plainly appearing to have inherited her Beauty, it was no difficult matter
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170135:41"/>for him who had ſeen <hi>Silvia,</hi> to diſcern this Lady to be her Mother: as ſhe was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing her great Obligements to him by a thouſand civil Complements, came in her Husband, who greatly deſiring to ſee his Daughter, ſpent not the time in many Ceremonies, but intreated him forthwith to bring him to the place where ſhe was. So they all went up ſtayrs toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where they found <hi>Silvia</hi> alone, and ſtartled at their ſudden ſurpriſing of her: after that with many expreſſions of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and affections on both ſides, and after they had ſolemniz'd with a great deal of Joy and Contentment, (and not without ſome Admiration) their being ſo happily met together, and ſo unexpectedly; and teſtified with infinite thanks, and large promiſes, their great obligations to <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> for his eminent Humanity and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: the mother of <hi>Silvia</hi> related to him the moſt remarkable things that had befallen her ſince ſhe parted from him; telling him, that after ſhe was return'd to her friends, there happened a diſaſter, which, for ſome years ſpace, depriv'd her of the ſatisfaction of her husbands ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty otherwiſe then by the mediation of Letters: for he having kill'd a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Salamanca,</hi> one of the moſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170135:42"/>of that place, was forc'd to retire him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a remore place, where he might be out of the reach of Juſtice, until ſuch time as his Majeſtie ſhould be pleas'd to grant him a Pardon: the time of his ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment being expir'd, he return'd home to his Country and Friends, where he liv'd in great honour and eſteem, wanting nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riches, nor any other contentment, but the ſociety of her, without whom all other comforts were but diſtaſteful; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, making known his reſolution to his friends, he came with all ſpeed to <hi>Granada,</hi> to ſee if my parents, having by this time remitted any thing of their rigorous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, would at length conſent that I ſhould be married to him; but found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing abated of their wonted ſeverity. We ſeeing them ſtill ſo obſtinately bent, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſteal away privately, one night, out of <hi>Granada,</hi> and to betake our ſelves to <hi>Madrid,</hi> where we might undiſturbed live together; and to call here by the way, to take our daughter along with us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Albanio,</hi> though he was ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to part with her, eſteeming her, for the many vertuous qualities ſhe poſſeſs'd, as dearly, as if ſhe had been his own daughter; yet ſeeing that there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meary, he told them, That whenever they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170135:42"/>pleas'd, he was ready to reſigne up his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in her to them. They anſwered, that in regard the longer they ſtay'd there, the greater their danger would be, in caſe her Parents, miſſing her, ſhould ſend after them, to bring them back; it would be neceſſary to make as little delay as might be, and therefore deſired that <hi>Silvia</hi> might be ready to take her journey with them the next morning by break of day.</p>
            <p>This unexpected news of the neceſſity of her ſo ſudden departure, affected <hi>Silvia</hi> in ſuch ſort, as that ſhe wiſh'd Heaven had been ſo favorable to her, as that ſhe might have been born to no other condition than that wherein ſhe had lived all this while; ſince the advancement of her Fortune tended to no leſs a prejudice to her, than the depriving her of him whom ſhe lov'd above all the world; conſtraining them to live ſo far apart, that her eyes ſhould henceforth be debar'd the deareſt object of their ſight. She labour'd all that in her lay, to get repeal'd the rigorous ſentence which was determin'd of her; ſometimes perſwading their abode there, ſometimes framing an excuſe that ſhe might be left behinde: but it little avail'd her; for her father and mother were induc'd to perſiſt in their determination, both by fear and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170135:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170135:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170135:44"/>love: fear, leſt if they ſhould be purſu'd, their ſtay there might cauſe them to be taken; love, which ſuffer'd them not to leave her behinde, for whom they had ſo tender an affection. So that, with a kinde of unwilling conſent, ſhe at laſt ſubmitted to the pleaſure of her parents: and when the very time of parting came, ſhe, all drown'd in tears, and with a heart over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd in grief, took her leave of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banio;</hi> intreating him, in the preſence of that maid ſhe rely'd ſo much in, and made the confident of all her counſels, That out of the reſpect he always bare her, he would certifie <hi>Cardenio</hi> of the unexpected occaſion of her ſudden departure from thence, without ſo much as bidding him Farewel. <hi>Albanio,</hi> although ſeriouſly taking upon him the truſt of this Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and conjur'd by all the tyes of Friendſhip, beſides his ſolemn promiſe, which in truth was made, onely to content her, and diſmiſs her with the greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and ſerenity of minde; yet when he conſider'd, that to perform this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, was a thing, however pleaſing to her humour, yet conducing to her diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; he judg'd it a friendly part in him to omit it. <hi>Silvia,</hi> (though accompany'd with ſo near Relations) while ſhe was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170135:44"/>her Journey toward <hi>Madrid,</hi> you may imagine in a moſt dejected poſture, her eyes over-ſhadow'd with a melancholy ſo obſcure, as nothing but the ſadneſſe of her minde could equal; each ſtep ſhe went, ſhe thought upon him who was the Soul of her Thoughts; and as oft as ſhe look'd back, perſwaded her ſelf ſhe ſaw him who was far enough off from her real ſight: but when her ſecond Thoughts, like a true friend, dealt really with her, and undeceiv'd her Fancy, ſhe began to be angry with her firſt Imagination, for deluding her with falſe appearances.</p>
            <p>In this juncture of time, was the minde of <hi>Cardenio</hi> agitated with a thouſand diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet Thoughts, when he perceiv'd, after his being recover'd, and well able to walk abroad, <hi>Silvia</hi> ſo regardleſſe of the Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which ſhe her ſelf had appointed, to talk with him, as ſhe ſent him word, about many things that concern'd him, which by this time was more than expir'd; he had not long remain'd in this ſuſpence, when it was murmur'd abroad, That ſhe was miſſing in her Fathers houſe, (for ſo was <hi>Albanio</hi> reputed) and that ſhe was privately gone away with one who had lately profeſs'd love unto her: ſo uſual a thing it is with the vulgar, to report
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170135:45"/>things otherwiſe than they really are, both by perverting the truth it ſelf, and by adding a hundred Fictions of their own unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardenio</hi> yet conſidered, That to have lent too eaſie a belief to the raſh ſurmiſes of the multitude, had been unworthy the Favours he receiv'd from <hi>Silvia;</hi> and that to conclude ill of any Woman from a ſlight information only, was to accuſe her in point of Honour, and to ſhew but a ſlender Opinion of her Vertue: but when he ſaw that what was lately but whiſper'd abroad, was now become the general and loud talk of people; and had inform'd himſelf for a certain, That ſhe was not at <hi>Albanio</hi>'s houſe; he then gave in his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage to the common voyce of Fame; ſuſpecting, that her appointing to meet him, at ſuch a certain time, was no other than a meer colour, that ſhe might have all that intire to her ſelf, for the more cloſe carriage of her dark deſign, in contriving a ſafe ſlight with the ſecret poſſeſſour of her beauty: he was reſtleſſe in every place, complain'd to Heaven, call'd upon death, rail'd, not only againſt <hi>Silvia,</hi> but the whole Race of Women<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; It hapning frequently in ſuchlike paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that the whole Sex bears both the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170135:45"/>blame and the curſe of one Womans miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage. <q>Ah (ſaid he, tranſported with fury) cruel Murtherers, pitileſſe to thoſe that love ye, kind to thoſe that hate ye; who would not deſire to live from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, to be free from your inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies and deceits? I have always in my minde thoſe words of <hi>Marcus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> where having occaſion to ſpeak of your exorbitancies, he breaks out into this exclamation: O Women! as oft as I call to remembrance that I had my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from you, I am out of conceit with life; and when I bethink me that I live among you, I long for death. <hi>Aurelius</hi> ſpoke diſcreetly, and like a Philoſopher, and one that had experience; ſuffering at that time by the ingratitude of <hi>Fauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> Ye ſay that we are inconſtant, and I believe it; not that we out of any volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary choice of our own, are culpable herein; but it is confer'd upon us by you, by reaſon of that infection we draw from you before we come into the world: Ye are always making Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, yet we always the offended par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: as there is a hidden power in your eyes, which forceth men to pity; ſo your tears can always force credit to your diſſimulations: when ye ſpeak of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170135:46"/>all men in general, ye beſpatter our Fames with ſome ignominious imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; when of one man ſingly, he is ſure to be flatter'd or traduc'd. Ah <hi>Silvia!</hi> inconſtant and unchaſte <hi>Silvia!</hi> did not I hear you one night ſo bitterly inveigh againſt all thoſe that had any ignoble or unworthy intentions, that I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd to think <hi>Lucretia</hi> reviv'd, or that another <hi>Penelope</hi> was come to live in the world? But I know too well, that this was ſpoken by you, only to gain a plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible eſteem among men: for as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to moſt, however vicious they be, to deſire to be thought vertuous; ſo eſpecially to Women, be they never ſo wavering, the opinion of Conſtancy is not unpleaſing; they loving to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for that very good quality wherein they are moſt defective. But indeed it cannot be imagin'd, that you ſhould recede from thoſe qualities which are inherent to your Sex; yet with what confidence could you, ſo unconſtant your ſelf, accuſe me of fickleneſſe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a kind of Obligation upon me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that no Woman was ever Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minally falſe? and indeed, who would have thought that your Love had not been very firme and ſecure to me, that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170135:46"/>had but ſeen, how much ado you had to forbear weeping through the force of your jealouſie; if it were jealouſie, and not much rather Envie? perhaps it griev'd you to ſee me apply my ſelf to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, not ſo much becauſe you lov'd me, as becauſe you could not endure that I ſhould diſeſteem you. Oh ingrateful! how ill am I repaid for thoſe tender Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances wherewith I have ſo often caſt my ſelf at your feet! For your ſake did I abandon my Country, my Friends, the garb wherein I liv'd: For your ſake did I confine my ſelf to this ſolitary place; and degrading my ſelf of the Honours of Court, that I might be advanc'd in your eſteem, I condeſcended to live with you in a quality equal to what yours repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and aſſum'd the Habit of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Swain: Methinks theſe Careſſes were worthy to have been acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, if not recompens'd. But, Fool that I am, to require the mindfulneſſe of Benefits, from a breſt ſo utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being generous.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus did the miſdeeming <hi>Cardenio,</hi> complain him of the conceived falſeneſſe of his adored <hi>Silvia.</hi> But, had the truth been known, he had little reaſon; for ſhe lov'd him with that zeal and fidelity, that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170135:47"/>there paſt not a moment wherein he was not paſſionately remembred of her: She on the other ſide thinking her ſelf forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of <hi>Cardenio</hi> (for miſtakes are ever ſtrongeſt at a diſtance) fear'd leſt he was grown remiſs and cool in that Love which he both pretended to her, and her Favours deſerved from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Albanio</hi> uſing often to go to <hi>Madrid,</hi> ſhe one time demanded of him, Whether he had made <hi>Cardenio</hi> acquainted with her being there, and with thoſe things ſhe ſpoke to him at her departure? He, to ſtop the Current of her Affections toward him, Anſwer'd, that Yes: and that he had wearied himſelf with often asking, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would come to ſee her? But that he, his thoughts being confounded in the labyrinth of a new Love, had ſcarce lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to afford him an Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silvia</hi> gave too facile a credit to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banio</hi>'s untruths; and being much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd againſt <hi>Cardenio,</hi> ſhe for his Crime, took ſharp revenge of her own fair eyes, putting them to a vaſt expence of tears. This hapned about that time when the Parents of <hi>Silvia</hi> were preparing to Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate their Nuptials; and ſhe having chang'd her Shepherdeſſes ſtate for the gayetie of a ſplendid Court, the luſtre of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170135:47"/>her natural Beauty, was heightned with all the advantages that Art and Glory could add unto it; and had already ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du'd to her chains ſuch Captives as might have tempted the conſtancy of any Lady leſs vertuous than her ſelf. <hi>Cardenio</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in vain long expected the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of <hi>Silvia</hi>'s Agreement, he reſented with ſo much rage her unfaithful breach of that performance, that he had not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to expect any longer; ſo that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing love for prompting him to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies, he quit his Shepherds crook, and returned back to <hi>Madrid,</hi> to ſhine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in his own proper ſphere of Gentil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Gallantry.</p>
            <p>Not long after his return, chancing to walk out into a Meadow one evening, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd with one Gentleman only, his Friend, one that lov'd to quarrel in the night, and keep houſe in the day-time, they ſaw coming toward them a Lady, who, both by her being alone, and by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of her walking, gave them to ſuſpect, that ſome diſcontent or other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted her minde. She had upon her head a Lion-coloured ſilken Vail, which caſt ſo great an umbrage over her, that it could not be diſcern'd who ſhe was; but the Skirt of her Gown overlay'd with a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170135:48"/>coſtly imbroydery, induc'd them to think that ſhe was a Lady, if not of higheſt rank, yet at leaſt of no mean degree: &amp; coming toward her, they aſſured her, <hi>That if ought lay in them wherein they could ſerve her, ſhe might command it. That you would both of you be pleaſed</hi> (anſwered the Lady) <hi>to follow me, I entreat, not command: It concerns me</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>to be avenged in the higheſt meaſure upon a man who hath offered ſo notorious a diſgrace, that it is enough to make me the ſubject of the Worlds laughter; nor can I be at quiet, till this injury be rated at the price of his blood.</hi> They led her between them, and walk'd ſeveral rounds about the Meadow; but could not finde the Man they look'd for. As they were returning homewards, a Coach which ſtay'd at the Monaſtery of <hi>Eſpiritu ſancto,</hi> wherein there were four Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and four Muſitians ſinging very loud in parts, caus'd them to ſtay their courſe; and that they might the more commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly hear the Muſick, they ſeated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the ſteps of the Church. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Muſick had ceas'd, and the Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had driven as far as the Fountains of St. <hi>Jeronimo,</hi> one of the Gallants within, chancing to ſpy the Lady, bid him, Stay his Coach; and alighting, made toward the Lady, to ſee who ſhe was: <hi>Cardenio</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170135:48"/>ſwelling with anger, withheld him from ſeeing her, ſaying, <hi>That ſuch a kinde of rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was not allow'd of at Court. I eſteem my ſelf</hi> (anſwered the Gentleman) <hi>not ſo ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, nor ſo little a Courtier, as to have need of your advice how to behave my ſelf; but Love, eſpecially back'd with Jealouſie, ſtands not upon nice punctillo's. The Lady in your company</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is mine; and though taking ſome diſtaſte at me, ſhe ſeem to forſake me, yet I claim her as my own. All that I am to take notice of,</hi> (replied <hi>Cardenio</hi>) <hi>is, That ſhe is at this time in my power, and caſt her ſelf upon my protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; therefore it concerns me to defend her from the violence of whoever ſhall pretend any right unto her.</hi> Thus there paſs'd many Replies from one ſide to the other; and the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants within the Coach ſomewhat the more confident, becauſe of their greater number, were not ſparing in their taunts and jeers. <hi>Cardenio</hi> and his Friend diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd to put up ſuch ſharp affronts; and thinking it ſurer with Swords than words to decide the Controverſie, began to draw upon them. Of the two that <hi>Cardenio</hi> had to deal with, one, after a ſhort diſpute, fell down at his ſeet, crying out that he was ſlain. No ſooner was it perceiv'd that he was diſpatch'd, but all the reſt of them fled away, cautious of the danger
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170135:49"/>that might enſue, if the Law of Duel ſhould be infring'd; which was, that as ſoon as any one man fell, the reſt ſhould deſiſt from farther violence, and retreat: <hi>Cardenio,</hi> only that he might not render himſelf ſuſpected, made no extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry haſte away; but leaving that ſtreet where the Quarrel was manag'd, took ſanctuary in the next houſe he ſaw open; deſiring the Favour of thoſe within, That he might there reſt himſelf ſecure from the malice of ſome that ſought his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. A Servant of the houſe, who had been an eye-witneſſe how valiantly he behav'd himſelf in the Combate, led him to an innermoſt Chamber, (at one end of which, there was a Door which op'ned into the Room where his Maſter and Miſtris uſed to be) where he might remain conceal'd from the ſearch of Juſtice, in caſe he were purſu'd. Leaving him there, and promiſing to afford him all the aſſiſtance he could, he lock'd the Chamber-door upon him, and went forth to ſee if he could gather, by learning out how the Report went of it about the Town, what this iſſue of the Fray was likely to prove; that according as he heard of it, he might the better know how to adviſe him for his ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170135:49"/>
Meanwhile <hi>Cardenio,</hi> left all alone and penſive, in an unknown obſcure place, had leaſure to contemplate upon his adverſe Fortune, and the miſchances that every moment attended him; but more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, he reflected upon the many troubles and inconveniencies which <hi>Silvia</hi>'s un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe had coſt him: and being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to counſel himſelf to forget the love that was ſo fruitleſſe, and had been ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to him; he heard from the next room the delicate ſound of a Womans ſhrill Complaints, which interſtop'd with many a heavie ſigh and groan, argued her the ſubject of ſome unſpeakable grief: His curioſity to know what it was, gave a breathing place to his own ſad thoughts, and made him deeply attentive to what ſhe ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ay me</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>what hath this poor beauty of mine (if it be ſuch as may deſerve that name) profited me? or rather, how much hath it not injur'd me, by betraying my heart to him that is ſo ungrateful, and treats me with ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect? To what end have I ſo long gloriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted his powerful intreaties &amp; inveiglements, when in the end I could not forbear ſurrendring my ſelf to him who hath ſo ill requited me? What hath it avail'd me to diſſemble all this while the ardency of my love to him, ſince at
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170135:50"/>length I am come off with the ſhame of yielding my ſelf ſo quickly, and love without the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of bring lov'd again. Oh</hi> Cardenio! <hi>who would have thought, That that Woman who diſprais'd thee more juſtly than ſhe her ſelf imagin'd, ſhould ſo eaſily yield her ſelf a prey to thy falſe allurements? to perſwade, thou art very Eloquent; but how to ſhew Gratitude. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together inexpert; thy Words ſpeak thee Noble, thy Deeds act a Clown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardenio,</hi> to hear his name mention'd in a ſtrange place, was much amaz'd: yet he imagin'd that haply ſome other bearing his Name, though not his Fortune, might have been the occaſion of this complaint.</p>
            <p>By this time the Servant was return'd, aſſuring him, that he was now at liberty to go where he pleas'd: Juſtice being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the impriſonment of one of the Adverſaries. <hi>Cardenio</hi> gratifying the man with the expreſſions of real Thanks for what he had done, and the reward of ſome Crowns; demanded the Name of him he ſerv'd? The Servant told him. It was a Gentleman that came hither to be Married to a Lady, whom ſince he firſt lov'd, there are many years now paſt, as appears by that ſweet Pledge which they have brought along with them; a fair Daughter, born in the infancy of their
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170135:50"/>Love, not above three leagues from Court, who till now, hath in a mean Village al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes liv'd obſcure, and under the notion of a plain Country-Shepherdeſſe, until ſuch time as her Parents might with ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty own her.</p>
            <p>Theſe things <hi>Cardenio</hi> hear, as it were tranſported out of himſelf with wonder, to obſerve the ſtrange Story of <hi>Silvia</hi>'s Fortune; and turning to the Servant, he ſaid, <hi>Without doubt, this is the ſame Lady that I heard ſo tenderly complaining to her ſelf but even now. 'T is moſt likely to be her,</hi> (the Servant reply'd:) <hi>for ever ſince ſhe came to the City, ſhe bath been noted for her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsive ſadneſs; eft breaking forth into ſuch violent paſsions of grief, that it is by moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, her melancholy ariſeth from ſome ſtrong affection left behinde her, which yet aetains her heart at</hi> Pinto: <hi>and although ſhe created a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in moſt, that her perplexity was for the abſence of thoſe ſhepherdeſſes, her companions, whom her long converſation with them, had very much endeared to her affection; yet I, for my part, have ſome ground to think otherwiſe, becauſe many times I have heard her bitterly complaining of one whom ſhe calls</hi> Cardenio: <hi>therefore I preſume it is not her love onely of her abſent companions, that occaſions this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170135:51"/>
It was a Task ſufficient for <hi>Cardenio,</hi> to ſuppreſs that exceſſive Joy he conceiv'd, hearing thoſe happy tidings: but diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concealing it, he entreated the man that he would, if it were poſſible, bear this Meſſage from him to the Lady, That a Gentleman who was an intimate Friend to <hi>Cardenio,</hi> humbly deſir'd her ſhe would be pleas'd to give way that he might ſee her, and preſent her with a Letter from him. The Servant, though at firſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what cautious to attempt the carrying of that Meſſage to his Lady; yet oblig'd by <hi>Cardenio</hi>'s Gifts, and knowing that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſtrangeneſs ſhe might diſſemble at firſt, ſhe would quickly be perſwaded to come to the ſpeech of her Lover, went confidently to <hi>Silvia,</hi> (who was now call'd <hi>Donna Violanta)</hi> and deliver'd his Errant to her. <hi>Silvia</hi> was a little amaz'd; and the Conflict between her Love and Honour, bred ſome Demurs: but incited by the unreſiſtable force of Love, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to venture; and cauſing the door to be op'ned, ſhe came into the Chamber to him.</p>
            <p>Great was the Aſtoniſhment on both ſides, when they beheld one another in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits ſo different from thoſe wherein they were ſeen of one another laſt: you would
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170135:51"/>have thought they had felt the power of <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s head, and were become Marble with admiring. <hi>Silvia</hi> was inwardly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-joy'd, that ſhe had in her preſence him whom ſhe had given over for loſt: but his chang'd apparel would ſcarce permit her to give credit to her own eyes. <hi>Cardenio,</hi> on the other ſide, ſeeing her ſo differently attir'd, could not tell what to think of it. As for <hi>Silvia,</hi> ſhe imagin'd, that without doubt, <hi>Cardenio</hi> having learn'd the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her quality, leſt his ſuppos'd diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhould cauſe her to forgo her love, had aſſum'd to himſelf this Gentile garb; and ſo began largely to inſiſt how vain a thing it was to be taken with outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; ſaying, that to go in obſcure or ſplendid Apparel, avail'd little, either to the confirming or infringing of a well-grounded affection: and ſhe did not ſo much diſ-eſteem a mean habit, as ſhe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed a rich minde; neither was a Rural courtſhip ſo unpleaſing to her, as a Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Civil deportment was pleaſing: nor did ſhe think it a ſhame for her to confeſs, that ſhe would ſooner chuſe to love that man who was but of an obſcure quality, and conſtant, than the moſt accompliſh'd Gallant, and perfidious. And thinking to take revenge on him for his forgetfulneſs,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170135:52"/>ſhe continued her diſcourſe ſomewhat ſharply, ſaying, That ſince his meanneſs not ſo much diſhonour'd her, as his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs offended her, ſhe was not ſo greatly incenſed toward him for being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to her in condition, as becauſe ſhe ſaw him not correſpondent to her in firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſincerity of affection: however, in this, ſhe comſorted her ſelf, That ſhe hop'd ſhe ſhould be able rather to endure and conceal her afflictions, nay even to die, than to ſuffer her ſelf any more to be incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to his falſe pretenſions; the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of whoſe Ingratitude, might be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warning to her.</p>
            <p>More ſhe had ſaid, would her paſſion have given her leave: but what ſhe left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken, her eyes ſpake for her: for the violence of her ſorrow, not able to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd within her breſt, burſt forth in tears.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardenio</hi> was put to a ſtrange non-plus, hearing the undeſerved complaints which <hi>Silvia</hi> made of his ſurmis'd neglect; when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, from the very day that ſhe firſt forſook <hi>Pinto,</hi> he neither had receiv'd any meſſage from her, nor could he come to know, by means of <hi>Albanio,</hi> where her abode was. Wherefore he made her this Anſwer: That as to the Ingratitude and Unworthineſs ſhe alleadg'd againſt him, ſuch was his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170135:52"/>that it was needleſs for him to make any excuſe; and that he ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd her contentment before his own, that if ſhe had deſign'd to beſtow her Love up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome one more deſerving, he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yeeld to the hazarding his life, by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her in the power of ſome other man, whom her affection might have made choice of, than ſeek to enjoy her himſelf, as long as his happineſs ſhould be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with her repoſe: yet, that ſhe might be undeceiv'd in the opinion ſhe had both of his condition, and his want of loyalty toward her; he told her, That whereas he had all this while gone under the name of <hi>Cardenio,</hi> and the form of a Country-villager, he was both of a quality Nobler than what he had hitherto profeſs'd, and his right name was <hi>Don Oſorio;</hi> and that (to make the credit of what he alleadg'd the more indiſputable, it was ſufficient to ſay, he was ally'd unto the Houſe of <hi>Lemos;</hi> and that it was he who paſſing one time thorow <hi>Pinto,</hi> and eſpying her, became a captive to her beauty; and impatient till he had obtain'd the oportunity of an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs unto her, came one night into her company, though through the nights ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, he was ſcarce able to diſcern her: but that afterwards, to gain frequent opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170135:53"/>of ſeeing her, and to have time to make his paſſion known, by the moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſervices he could be capable of rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to her, he had put on that ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-diſguiſe, in which he ſo oft appear'd to her: and that however ſhe was pleas'd to inveigh againſt his neglect of her, he had ever remain'd a Rock in that ſincerity he firſt profeſs'd; and at that very time when it was rumour'd abroad that ſhe was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from <hi>Albanio</hi>'s houſe, he was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly perplex'd about it, ſeeing all men whiſper and entertain odde conceits about it: but when neither from <hi>Albanio,</hi> nor any one elſe, he could receive the certainty of what was the occaſion of her departure, nor whither ſhe was remov'd; he thought it needleſs to ſtay any longer here, and ſo return'd back to Court; and walking forth one evening with a friend, he chanced to be engaged in a Quarrel, in which one of the adverſaries fell; and that he fleeing from the ſeverity of Juſtice, was by his good Genius happily directed to this houſe, where hearing his name repeated among many ſighs and complaints, he came to be inform'd of the whole Story of her proceedings; and, that he remain'd abſolutely devoted to her command, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not to diſpoſe of himſelf in any way
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170135:53"/>that ſhould not ſubmit to her concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or afford him the opportunities of having the honour to ſerve her: and that ſhe might the better ſatisfie her ſelf of the reality of his affection, he pray'd her to conſider that he had not altogetherdeclin'd the acting of what might in ſome ſort pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to her eſteem; having deveſted himſelf of his own Quality for her ſake, whom he abſolutely concluded to be his inferiour: whereas ſhe on the other ſide, ſince the late change of her Fortune, had out of the ſame conſideration, ſought to retract her long-profeſs'd Love. To which ſhe anſwered, That notwithſtanding the Reverend old Man, who in her eſteem had ever had the place of a Father, had long ſince reveal'd to her whoſe child ſhe was, &amp; withal ſtrictly admoniſh'd her, that having regard to her Modeſty and Honour, ſhe ſhould not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any one beneath her in degree; yet that ſhe remain'd conſtant and unmov'd in that Affection, which took beginning in her, from that night forward, wherein he having obtained an opportunity of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing himſelf to her, made ſo large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of his Love. And that he might ſee how much the reality of her Love pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed above the thought of her Quality, ſhe gave him a Letter to read which ſhe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170135:54"/>had written at <hi>Pinto,</hi> thinking to have left it behinde her, to be ſent him by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banio,</hi> as a teſtimony of her conſtancy: the Letter <hi>Cardenio</hi> read, it being to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Violanta</hi> to <hi>Cardenio.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>If with the change of my Habit and Fortune, I had chang'd that Love which I have ſo long borne you, I might ſeem to have done that which the reſpect of Blood and greatneſs oblig'd me to; but ſo far am I from the leaſt thought of forſaking you, that I was never more firmly than now, reſolv'd to be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yours: he that gives you this, will give you an account of my condition, and the reaſon of my departure. Reſt happy, and aſſur'd, that though at preſent the diſtance between our qualities be as great as that which ſeparates our ſelves, my Love ſhall make you Noble, and render you worthy of my Nuptials.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Violanta.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardenio</hi> had no longer what to doubt, nor <hi>Silvia</hi> what to fear: that night he kept in the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170135:54"/>ſame Lodging, <hi>Silvia</hi>'s care not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, for fear of whatſoever danger might befal him, to ſtir out of the Houſe. The next morning ſhe went to her Father and Mother, acquainted them with the whole proceedings of their loves, and all the circumſtances that had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: they making it their own caſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo freſh in Memory the powerful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Love in themſelves; wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, That to croſs a Woman in her deſires, is to drive her into remedileſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences; her Father alſo knowing <hi>Cardenio</hi> to be a man highly eſteem'd of in Court, for his great Quality and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Vertues, they gave their free conſent that they ſhould be married. About the ſame time, it fortun'd that their Parents al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo came from <hi>Granada</hi> to <hi>Madrid;</hi> who when they ſaw, that their Daughter match'd to ſo noble a Gentleman, and the Fruits of their lawful Loves appearing in ſo beautiful a Pledge, whom, not without great admiration they beheld, they were ſo far from continuing their former averſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, knowing it in vain to repine againſt that which Heaven hath decreed ſhould come to paſs, that they chang'd their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure into content, their anger into gladneſs. <hi>Cardenio</hi> enjoy'd his beloved
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170135:55"/>
               <hi>Silvia:</hi> and the ſtrangeneſs of their Loves adventure, being publiſh'd through the Court, their Nuptials were ſolemniz'd with a great deal of Joy; all Men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauding the happineſs of <hi>Cardenio,</hi> and the Divine Beauty of <hi>Silvia,</hi> now a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Lady of the Court, who was lately a mean Shepherdeſs of <hi>Pinto.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170135:55"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Theſe Books following are Printed by <hi>Nath. Brook,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TImes Treaſury or Academy for the Gentry, for their accompliſhment in Arguments of diſcourſe, habit, faſhion: ſummed up all in a Character of Honour. By <hi>Ri. Brathwait,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>That excellent piece of Phyſiognomy and Chiromancy, Metopoſcopy, the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical Proportion and Signal Moles of the Body; the ſubject of Dreams: to which is added, The Art of Memory. By <hi>Ri. Sanders.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>Magick Aſtrology vindicated, by <hi>H. Warren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fons Lacrymarum:</hi> or, a Fountain of Tears, with an Elegy upon Sir <hi>Charls Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> By <hi>J. Quarles.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Contentation, fit for theſe ſad and troubleſome times. By <hi>Ioſ Hall,</hi> late B. of <hi>Exon</hi> and <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:170135:56"/>
Mirrour of Complements, ſitted for Ladies, Gentlewomen, Scholars, and Strangers; with forms of ſpeaking and writing of Letters moſt in faſhion: with witty Poems, and a Table expounding hard Engliſh words.</p>
            <p>Divinity no Enemy to Aſtrology: A Sermon for the Society of Aſtrologers for the year 1653. By Dr. <hi>Thomas Swadlin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Select Thoughts: or, Choice Helps For a pious Spirit, beholding the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of her Lord Jeſus. By <hi>J. Hall,</hi> B. of <hi>Norwich.</hi> A new piece.</p>
            <p>The Holy Order, or Fraternity of Mourners in <hi>Zion.</hi> To which is added Songs in the Night: or, Chearfulneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Affliction. By <hi>Joſ. Hall,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi> A new piece.</p>
            <p>The Art of Memory: a cure for a weak Memory, uſeful for all perſons, from the Gown to the Clown. A new piece.</p>
            <p>That complete piece called the Exact Surveyor of Land, ſhewing how to plot all manner of Grounds, and to reduce and divide the ſame. Alſo Iriſh meaſure, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to Engliſh ſtatute-meaſure; uſeful for all that either ſell or purchaſe. By <hi>I. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Milk for Children: or, A plain and eafie Method of teaching to Read and to Write, with brief Rules for School-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb facs="tcp:170135:56"/>to inſtruct their Scholars in, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to inſtruct their Families in, by Dr. <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Culpepers</hi> Phyſical and Chyrurgical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, of his own admired Experience, never publiſhed before now by his Wife, being his laſt Legacies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Culpepers Semiotica:</hi> or, his Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Judgment of Diſeaſes, much enlarged, from the Decumbiture of the ſick, which way to finde out the Cauſe, Change, and End of the Diſeaſes. Alſo whether the ſick be likely to live or die: With the ſigns of life and death by the body of the ſick party, according to the Judgment of <hi>Hipporcates.</hi> With a Treatiſe of Urines, by <hi>N. Culpeper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> his fourth Book of <hi>Occult</hi> Philoſophy, of <hi>Geomancy:</hi> Magical Elements of <hi>Peter de Abano,</hi> the nature of Spirits, made Engliſh by <hi>R. Turner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pulpit Sparks, being ſet forms of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers uſed before Sermon, by Dr. <hi>Jeremiah Taylor,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gillingham,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hewit,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Eminent Divines.</p>
            <p>The Queens Cloſet opened. Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſecrets in Phyſick, Chyrurgery; preſerving, candying, and cooking, as they were preſented to the Queen: tranſcribed from the true Copies of her Majeſties own
<pb facs="tcp:170135:57"/>receipt-Books by <hi>W. M.</hi> one of her late Servants.</p>
            <p>The Conveyancers Light, or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Clark and Scrivener's Guide, being an Exact draught of all Preſidents and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances now in uſe, as they were penned and perfected by divers Learned Judges, eminent Lawyers, and great Conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, both antient and modern; whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is added a Coneordance from <hi>K. Rich.</hi> 3. to this preſent.</p>
            <p>Wits Interpreter, the Engliſh <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> or a ſure Guide to thoſe admirable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, that complete our Engliſh Gentry in the moſt acceptable qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Diſcouſe or Writing: Alſo the whole Myſtery of thoſe pleaſing Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts of Eloquence and Love are made eaſie, in the Art of Reaſoning, Theatre of Courtſhip, Labyrinth of Fancies, Love-Songs, Drollery; The perfect Inditer of Letters, <hi>A lamode,</hi> by <hi>I. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Floating Iſland, a Tragedy-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy acted before the King, by the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of <hi>Chriſt-Church.</hi> by Dr. <hi>Strond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wit and Drollery: with other Jovial Poems.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paracelſus</hi> of Occult Philoſophy, or his Secrets of Nature.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
